<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The redemption of lost time</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 140 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841470</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841470</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 717:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The redemption of lost time</title>
                  <author>Powel, Daniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 130 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. O[kes] for Richard Sergier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Daniel Powel.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The REDEMPTION of loſt Time.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Epheſ. <hi>5.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Redeeme</hi> the <hi>Time,</hi> for the daies are euill.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>N.O.</hi> for <hi>Richard Sergier.</hi> 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE SIR EDWARD COKE KNIGHT, LORD chiefe Iuſtice of the Kings Maieſties Court of Comon Plees.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ouchſafe my good Lord, to patronage this ſmall Treatiſe of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of loſt
<pb facs="tcp:6055:3"/>Time,</hi> which heere I preſent vnto your Honor (as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted token of my dutifull affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you) not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming thereby to inſtruct your Lo. in any thing you lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not before, being a Perſon wel known to haue deepe inſight in the due value and
<pb facs="tcp:6055:3"/>worth of <hi>TIME,</hi> and wiſely to vnderſtand how to eſtimate, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy and diuide the ſame, rendring to euery action his due Time, and to euery Time, his right fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: But that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadowe of your wings and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, I may bee freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Taxe,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:4"/>whereof the beſt Bookes now adayes imprinted cannot e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape cenſure. And verily, if they bee commended whoe bring vs any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, drugges or delights, faſhions or fruits from forraine Countries, how can I be iuſtly reproued, if after long purſuit
<pb facs="tcp:6055:4"/>in a ſtrange land, J bring home a diſh of rare dainties, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and neceſſary, a pretious Iewell ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher then the gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of loſt Time.</hi> Thus cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to interrupte your Honors waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier buſineſses, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this vnto your
<pb facs="tcp:6055:5"/>Lordſh. fauour, and your Lordſh. to the Almightie his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi>
                  <date>the <hi>10.</hi> of <hi>May. 1608.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſh. humbly to command,</hi> Daniel Powel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true which is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Caſtilian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb, <hi>El bien no es conocido, haſta que es per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dido, The good is not knowen vntill it be lost;</hi> as I haue at laſt found by experience in my ſelfe, who haue, but ſince my late Trauels, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther apprehended what TIME is, nor vnderſtood the power and value there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: which verily doth not a little griue and vexe me,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:6"/>in that all this while I loſt ſo much good. Wherefore I could hartily deſire with the Poet,</p>
            <q>O ſi praeteritos referat mihi Iupiter annos!</q>
            <p>That, if it wre poſſible, I might once againe enioy the yeares that are already paſt, whereby I might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them as I ought, and redeeme them from the captiuitie wherein they haue beene detained. But he who once ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded to knowe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimate the Time as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained, is nowe well worthy to wiſh and want that which ſometimes he had in aboundance and
<pb facs="tcp:6055:6"/>vainely miſpent. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I hold it for a ſpeciall gift and grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me of GOD, that now at length he hath vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed me this knowledge, that henceforth I may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter imploy the time which the Lord in mercy ſhall hereafter graunt vnto me; and that now I throughly vnderſtand what it is to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to know God in Chriſt, to worſhip him only; to read the Scriptures, to heare Gods word, to be partaker of the Sacraments, and to pray in a knowne tongue; which I ſpeake not as if I had beene at any time affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:7"/>otherwiſe then now I am, but becauſe I neuer heretofore eſteemed either TIME, or any of theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites according to their iuſt value and worth, as now I do.</p>
            <p>And in this reſpect I could wiſh all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute me their Proctor &amp; Aduocate aſwell to ſue for their ranſome; as alſo to teach and inſtruct ſuch negligent Sinners as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Time</hi> captiuated, how they ought to <hi>Redeeme</hi> the ſame, &amp; how much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes and imports them; to admoniſh ſecure and careleſſe Chriſtians right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to waigh the Benefites
<pb facs="tcp:6055:7"/>which in great abundance GOD hath mercifully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon this Church and Common wealth; and to beſeech all others that they looſe neither houre nor moment of any Time or Seaſon.</p>
            <p>For accompliſhment whereof I deſire all men to peruſe this ſmall Manual, wherein they may plainely vnderſtand &amp; learne, both how and from what TIME is to be redeemed, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in what ſort they ought to imploy the ſame. And though haply ſome men may thinke that in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of TIME much Time may be ſpent (which
<pb facs="tcp:6055:8"/>though otherwiſe I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge may be true,) yet hold I not the Time imployde in this Treatiſe, either loſt or ill ſpent.</p>
            <p>I hartily pray and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech our Lord GOD, euen for his moſt precious bloud ſake (which was the price of our Redemption) that euen as I wiſh and deſire, ſo this <hi>Redemption of Time loſt,</hi> may be beneficiall and profitable to the Reader.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:8"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Chapters which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 1.</label> What a precious Iewell <hi>TIME</hi> is. <hi>Fol. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 2.</label> That we are <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> and to what end <hi>GOD</hi> did beſtow it vpon vs, and wherein we are to imploy the ſame. <hi>Fol. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 3.</label> How <hi>GOD</hi> in his iust Iudgement cutteth off ſinners from inioying the benefit of <hi>Time,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made no reckoning thereof to profit themſelues thereby, as they ought and might haue done. <hi>Fol. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 4.</label> He that now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyeth
<pb facs="tcp:6055:9"/>the Benefite of <hi>TIME,</hi> muſt with great feruencie and zeale labour to imploye it altogether well. <hi>Fol. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 5.</label> How worthy of reproofe idle Perſons are, and who they be. <hi>Fol. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 6.</label> How the <hi>BODY</hi> detaineth in captiuitie the Time which is properly the <hi>SOVLES,</hi> and how it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alts it ſelfe and rebelleth against the <hi>SOVLE. Fol. 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 7.</label> That lay perſons may lawfully enioy ſome recreations, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynements of mirth, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace and pleaſure. <hi>Fol. 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 8.</label> That likewiſe it is
<pb facs="tcp:6055:9"/>lawfull, yea very neceſſary for religious and eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall perſons to vſe ſome honeſt exerciſe, which may ſerue for intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, recreation and rest. <hi>Fol. 96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 9.</label> How <hi>TIME</hi> is to bee redeemed; and who they be that detaine the ſame in captiuity. <hi>Fol. 108.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. 10.</label> How it is to bee vnderſtood that <hi>the dayes are euill,</hi> and howe that therefore <hi>TIME</hi> is to be redeemed. <hi>Fol. 119.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:10"/>
            <head>EPIGRAMMA.</head>
            <l>PRimus vt antè liber docuit ſperare ſalutem,</l>
            <l>Tarda tui quamuis fuerit moeſtitia cordis,</l>
            <l>Dum ſyncera tamen: promit ſic docta ſecundus</l>
            <l>Dogmata, quêis diſcas â primo flore iuuentae</l>
            <l>Subdere colla Deo: rocte<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> impendere <hi>Tempus.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tempus,</hi> &amp; obrizo longè praeſtantius auro,</l>
            <l>Cui magnae cedat famae Carbunculus, atque</l>
            <l>Arcana quaecunque iacent tellure recluſa.</l>
            <l>Non ſi ſorte tibi non applaudente, reperta</l>
            <l>Diuitia pereant, ſpes est reuocare, volantis</l>
            <l>At non est horae fas inſtaurare ruinam.</l>
            <l>Obſeruat natura vices, rapiduſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> polorum</l>
            <l>Tempore tranſigitur curſus, fit circulus, atque</l>
            <l>Vertitur in gyrum rurſus, rurſuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> recurſat,</l>
            <l>Nec tamen vna redit tranſacti temporis hora.</l>
            <l>Resnullareuocanda prece, precióue, beatum</l>
            <l>Quae faciat, ſtygios aut certè mergat in amnes.</l>
            <l>Si tibi currenti fructus cum tempore cedit,</l>
            <l>Otiá declinas, remanent te praemia, verùm</l>
            <l>Si teris incautè <hi>Tempus,</hi> quando vltima tande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </l>
            <l>Hora aduentârit, fuerit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> occaſio caſsa</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtutis, lugens inferni clauſtra ſubibis.</l>
            <l>Ergo agè quando datu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, virtuti inſiſtere cura:</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t tutus Chriſtum valeas audire vocantem.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>G. B.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:10"/>
            <l>THE <hi>Paſt,</hi> the <hi>Preſent,</hi> and the <hi>Time to be</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Could a man tell, or were there mortall wight</l>
            <l>So farre aboue earth, raiſed to that hight</l>
            <l>That heauens dimenſions he could clearly ſee;</l>
            <l>Better that man were to report from thee</l>
            <l>The Benefites, mortallity might raiſe</l>
            <l>From thy iuſt labours, then th'vncertaine praiſe</l>
            <l>Attending books, which not their worth can free</l>
            <l>From the Taxation which foule <hi>Enuie</hi> laies</l>
            <l>On <hi>Vertues</hi> faire-ſelfe, and with helliſh ſpight</l>
            <l>Is euer blaſting the deſerued Bayes,</l>
            <l>That ſhould adorne her: But receiue this right</l>
            <l>From TIME it ſelfe that muſt thy fortreſſe be,</l>
            <l>Whoſe perfect vſe is onely taught by thee.</l>
            <bibl>M. Drayton.</bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:11"/>
            <head>The Authors (beſides ſacred Scriptures) who are cited in <hi>this preſent Treatiſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>Alphonſus de Castro.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Ambroſe.</item>
               <item>Andreas <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Caeſarea.</item>
               <item>Ariſtotle.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Auguſtine.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Baſil.</item>
               <item>Bede <hi>the venerable.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bernardinus de Sena.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Bernard.</item>
               <item>Bonauenture.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>Caſsianus.</item>
               <item>Ceſarius Heliſterbacchenſis.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Chryſoſtome.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Dion Caſsius.</item>
               <item>Dionyſius Carthuſianus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Elianus.</item>
               <item>Euthymius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:6055:11"/>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>Gregory Niſſen.</item>
               <item>Gregory <hi>the Pope.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>Haymo.</item>
               <item>Horace.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>S. Ierome.</item>
               <item>Iohn Chryſoſtome.</item>
               <item>Iohn Damaſcen.</item>
               <item>Iohn Orozeus.</item>
               <item>Iohn Stobeus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>Laertius.</item>
               <item>Laurence Iuſtinian.</item>
               <item>Ludouicus Bloſius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>Maldonatus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>Nicholas Diukeſpu.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>Origen.</item>
               <item>Ouid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>Plutarch.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:6055:12"/>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>Salmeron.</item>
               <item>Seneca.</item>
               <item>Simon de Caſsia.</item>
               <item>Suarez.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>Thaulerus.</item>
               <item>Theodoret.</item>
               <item>Thomas Aquinas.</item>
               <item>Thomas Kempis.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>Viegas.</item>
               <item>Virgil.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Z</head>
               <item>Zedrenus.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6055:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What a precious Iewel <hi>TIME</hi> is.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the maner and ſtile of the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any notable cauſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portancie is ſhewed and noted vnto vs, ſome won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull viſion or miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous type euer goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which doth awake &amp; ſtirre vp our ſpirits and ſenſes for attention, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them in ſuſpenſe and admiration, as very ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb facs="tcp:6055:13"/>may bee ſeene in the booke of the Prophets, and ſpecially in the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the bleſſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> where amongſt many other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable viſions &amp; ſtrange figures, chiefely that is to bee noted, which hee hath vvritten in the tenth Chapter (which together with thoſe wordes of the Apoſtle, in his Epiſtle to them of Epheſus,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Redeeme the Time, becauſe the dayes are euill;</hi> ſhall bee the very Theame or ground of this our Treatiſe and exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſaying,<note place="margin">Reue. 10.1.</note> that then <hi>hee ſawe a mightie Angell come downe from heauen, cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6055:13"/>with a cloude, and that hee wore vpon his heade,</hi> in ſteede of a Dyademe, <hi>the rainebow, and his face ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as the Sunne</hi> in midday, <hi>His feet were as pillers of fire, And he had in his hande a</hi> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Booke open,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and hee put his right foote vpon the Sea, and his left vpon the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3.</note> 
               <hi>And cried with a loud voice, after the maner of a Lyon when he roareth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5.</note> 
               <hi>and lifting vp his finger towards heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6.</note> 
               <hi>ſware by him that liueth for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, which created heauen, and the earth, and the Sea, &amp; all things in them contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That from the daies of the ſeauenth Angell, there ſhould neuer be any more</hi> TIME.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6055:14"/>
And briefly to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the myſteries which here are compriſed,<note place="margin">Refert illos Viegas in Apoc. cap. <hi>10</hi> Andreas Epiſc. Ceſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reae in c. <hi>5.</hi> Apoc. <hi>Act. 1.2.</hi>
               </note> This <hi>Angell</hi> according to the expoſition of many Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, is <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord; the Angell of the great Councell, or els is one of the bleſſed Angels which repreſenteth his perſon, and executeth the office of Legat-ſhip, as his Imbaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour. <hi>He came downe from Heauen,</hi> becauſe viſibly he is to diſcend from thence in a cloude ſhining with great power and maieſtie, to iudge the whole world: Howbeit, his comming <hi>clothed with a cloud,</hi> doth ſignifie the confuſion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6055:14"/>and turmoile which ſhall happen as well in thoſe laſt dayes, as alſo in that ſpace and time, in which the perſecution of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſhall indure: when ſpecially they ſhall behold thoſe hideous ſignes and terrible tokens, which are to happen before the day of the vniuerſall Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; are euery moment to expect that fearfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Iudge. The <hi>Raine-bow</hi> ſignifies peace; and the <hi>Fire,</hi> wrath, furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and puniſhment: and in thoſe two extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of mans body, which are, the feet, and the head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both the end and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:6055:15"/>thereof (viz.) both top &amp; toe, are pourtrayed both the commings of our Sauiour CHRIST into the world. The firſt was, of meere mercie, to make peace and attonement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and men; and becauſe of that, for his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutchion and ſpeciall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, hee bare vpon his head the <hi>Raine-bow</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in token that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of his former anger, diſpleaſure and paſſed pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, were now cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And in the latter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, hee ſhall come as Iudge, and therefore hee ſhall carrie feete of fire, which betokens inflexible
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6055:15"/>rigour, and terrible wrath: <hi>Ignis ante ipſum praecedet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.3.</note> ſaith <hi>Dauid, There ſhall goe before him a conſuming fire.</hi> The <hi>Forme</hi> and ſhape of the <hi>Pillars</hi> ſignifies, the mighty ſtrength and force he ſhall haue, for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his final ſentence and laſt Iudgement. <hi>The Booke open in his hand,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his God-head, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth the eternal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom he hath, for the which he appropriateth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the office of Iudge; &amp; in reſpect of his Manhood, it ſignifieth the abſolute knowledge he apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the worth &amp; worthines of the cauſes,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:16"/>proceſſe and actions of all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the ſcroll or proclamation of the diuine lawe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are to be iudged. <hi>The putting of one foote vpon the Sea, &amp; the other vpon the Land,</hi> is as much to ſay, as that he imbraceth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth &amp; comprehendeth all things, ſea and land, earth and water; &amp; that nothing can eſcape his hands, free it ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his power,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139. ver. 3. &amp; 8.</note> nor be hid from his preſence. <hi>The roaring, as of a Lyon,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the wrath and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, wherewith hee ſhall pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſentence againſt the condemned ones. And the <hi>ſolemne oath,</hi> ſignifieth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6055:16"/>the infallible certaintie &amp; aſſuredneſſe he ſhall haue, in the accompliſhment and execution of thoſe things before prophecied, &amp; preached to the people, which in the dayes of the ſeuenth Angell, when they ſhall heare that fearefull Trumpet ſounding and ſummoning all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> to Iudgement, ſhall ende and finiſh the <hi>Time</hi> for euer afterwardes; and they who made no profit thereof, when they had it, but haue deferred their good works vntill the vttermoſt day, &amp; laſt houre of their liues, ſhall eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remaine without it. And
<pb facs="tcp:6055:17"/>that <hi>publike ſounding and proclamation of the Angell,</hi> with ſuch and ſo many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, That on ſome day <hi>Time</hi> ſhould ende and ceaſe, &amp; when that ſhould be, is, to giue vs intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence that wee may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand of what price, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and eſtimation, and what a great benefite of God beſtowed vpon vs it is, that hee hath made vs <hi>Lords</hi> of the ſame all the dayes of our liues. And on the contrary, what a great croſſe and puniſhment is it, for otherſome to bee abſolutely bereaued therof and to haue it quite taken away from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as a thing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6055:17"/>by them miſpent, and ill imployed.</p>
            <p>To manifeſt what a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious thing <hi>Time</hi> ſhall be, it ſufficeth onely to know, that in one inſtance of time, one may gaine infinite eternitie of glorie. And therefore the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> counſaileth vs,<note place="margin">Eccli. 4.20.</note> to preſerue and keepe <hi>Time,</hi> as we doe gold, ſo ſhall we depart from euill; which is, as if he had told vs, that we ſhould vſe &amp; imploy it in good works, &amp; not looſe the leaſt moment thereof. Againe, he willeth vs to be aduiſed by the ſame <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccli. 14.14.</note> ſaying: <hi>Defraud not thy ſelfe of the good day, and
<pb facs="tcp:6055:18"/>let not the portion of the good deſires ouerpas thee.</hi> One tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation hath <hi>Particula bonae diei:</hi> &amp; others (as likewiſe in the vulgar editio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) <hi>Boni doni.</hi> One while he ſaith, let no part of the <hi>good day</hi> ouerpas thee for nought; another while he ſaith of the <hi>good gift, or deſires.</hi> The meaning is, to admoniſh vs, that we ſpend wel the <hi>Time,</hi> and the <hi>Day,</hi> yea all days: for he that can wel order &amp; redres one day may by the ſame ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and reforme al his life, &amp; in the ſame, man ought to do all the good he can for him ſelfe, &amp; for his neighbors, exerciſing himſelf in works of Pietie and mercie. King
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6055:18"/>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo much feared to looſe the leaſt particle of <hi>Time,</hi> &amp; ſo farre indeuored wholy to imploy the ſame wel, that he ſtriued &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with the ſun, for ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpriſing to praiſe God, which at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth the king pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uented, according to thoſe words,<note place="margin">Pſal. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ver. 147.148</note> 
               <hi>Praeueneru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t oculi mei ad te diluculo. Early in the morning do I cry vnto thee: Mine eies preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the morning watch, that I might meditate in thy words: for before the Sun was vp, I was occupied in the ſame.</hi> Which according to the expoſition of S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> is as much as if more clearely hee had ſpoken, Riſe earlier thou Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:19"/>before the Sun be vp, for I hold it great neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; careleſneſſe moſt culpable in thee, that the beames of the Sunne when it riſeth, ſhould find thee idle and ſleeping in thy bed. Thou art ignorant perhaps, that thou oughteſt euery day to render vnto God almighty the firſt fruits of thy toung and heart? See thou haue a daily harueſt, and daily fruite in like maner. And in another Pſalme, the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.4.</note> 
               <hi>Anticipaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt vigilias oculi mei.</hi> My eyes preuented, and awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before the watch-men, and gard of the citie: that is to ſay, (as <hi>S. Ierome</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6055:19"/>before that any body went to watch, or did awake, I awaked and watched at midnight and in the morning, at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day &amp; in the euening; and finally ſeuen times a day doe I laud my Lorde, yea, alwayes and at all houres haue I his prayſes in my mouth. Hee well knew how to obſerue <hi>Time,</hi> hee duely acknowledged what it was, and what ſtood him auaileable; &amp; as of a thing ſo pretious, hee knew how to make profite thereof, without looſing one iot ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Good day,</hi> or of the <hi>good gift. Time</hi> ſaith <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> is a moſt coſtly<note place="margin">Theophraſt.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6055:20"/>expenſe.<note place="margin">Seneca. Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Seneca</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle (which hee wrote to his friend <hi>Lucili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>) ſaith thus; What man is he, that will ſuffer me to ſet price on his Time? How much thinkes hee, is the day worth, admitting that euery day hee were to die? wherfore we do much deceiue our ſelues herein, becauſe we fix not our eies vpon death, a great part whereof is already paſt; all that of our age &amp; life which yet remaineth behinde, death holdes in poſſeſſion. Wherfore my deere friend <hi>Lucilius,</hi> perſiſt ſtill in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that which thou thy ſelfe in thy Letters, didſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6055:20"/>write vnto me thou doeſt, being a perſon that ſo well knoweſt the due eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Time: imbrace al the houres, ſo ſhalt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend leſſe vppon the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, pointing (as it were) this day with thy finger, not permitting the ſame to ouerpaſſe thee idlely, for the life (putting it ſelfe off with prolonging) flies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way &amp; paſſeth at random; And all things els beeing eſtrainged &amp; alienated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, onely <hi>Time</hi> is ours; and very naturall reaſon hath infourmed vs, that we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the poſſeſſion of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſwift thing, which run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth away ſo faſt, and ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:6055:21"/>amaine, yea flyes apace from betweene our hands. The knowledge and diſcretion of mortall men is ſo litle and weake, that they impute it a great loſſe incaſe they leaue vndone the leaſt vileſt thing, or ſmalleſt trifle, being indeed reuocable and amendable though pretermitted, none thinkes that hee oweth or is indebted any thing for hauing receiued Time, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that <hi>Time</hi> is but one ſole thing, which yet the gratefull ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can make no due ſatiſfaction for that which he receiued as hee ought, in regard of the high price, and for that the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6055:21"/>debt is great in vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the day vpon himſelf. And in his booke of the ſhortneſſe of life,<note place="margin">Idem lib. de breuit vitae.</note> he ſaith: There is no man that will forgoe or part with his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie or ſubſtance, nor diſinherite himſelfe, but rather will keepe it, and augment it: as for Time, and his courſe of life, hee will with great facility im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and beſtow them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times on diuerſe vaine things. They are very nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their wealth, but for Time they are moſt prodigall and lauiſh, when as indeed their honeſt and laudable couetouſneſſe, ſhould be onely of Time;
<pb facs="tcp:6055:22"/>becauſe moſt truely (as in the ſame Booke, then preſently after hee ſaith: Time is the moſt precious thing that is, and yet for al that, they diſpraiſe it and hold it of no eſteeme, for nought, and of no worth; as though it were right nought indeed, bearing no price at all. Not one makes reckoning of it when they haue it, but if any be ſicke, then ſhall you ſee bowing of knees &amp; crouching be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Phyſitian, and if hee feare the ſentence of death, that man will waigh him with gold for to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome his life,</p>
            <p>That bleſſed holy man,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6055:22"/>
               <hi>Laurentius Iuſtinianus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Laur. Iuſt. de vitae ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. <hi>6.10.</hi>
               </note> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Time and the value thereof, ſayeth thus: Who hath that power to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend or conceiue in his heart, what a precious thing Time is? O what grace, eloquence or ſweet flowing ſpeach of man is able to declare it? None knowes it, but ſuch as now want and miſſe the ſame. Then all the goods of the world, honours, dignities, and prelacies, the pompe of this age, corporall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and bodily pleaſures yea and all maner recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſports and paſtimes, ioyes and intertainements whatſoeuer they be, which
<pb facs="tcp:6055:23"/>are vnder the cope of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, would bee giuen in boote and exchanged for one houre of Time, if it were poſſible to bee obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; becauſe in this moſt ſhort ſpace, they would appeaſe the diuine Iuſtice, they would make glad and reioyce the Angels, they would eſchewe from that fearefull ſentence of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation, and gaine (yea without al doubt they would procure) life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. And they are moſt vnhappie, vpon whom the Sunne of mercie is already ſet, who moſt irreuocably ſhall deſcend into that lake of miſerie, where there is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6055:23"/>neither <hi>order</hi> nor good courſe,<note place="margin">Iob. 10.15. &amp; 22,</note> but fright and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror perpetuall, and with good reaſon ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed of their pardon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their contempt and diſdaining of Time when it was offered them, who reſpected neither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration nor the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the validitie and worthineſſe of the ſame, nor yet the great neceſſitie &amp; lacke therof, which one day they ſhould feele, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing after the taſte of their pallats and proofe of their appetites, as though they ſhould neuer dye. Oh I would to God, that they who imploy the time wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:24"/>and liue moſt idlely &amp; ſecurely, did know how to eſtimat that, which they ouerpaſſe, and looke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration and due regarde. For what thing is it that is more valuable then Time? what thing more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? what thing more ſeemly &amp; cheerfull? what thing of more fruit and better profite? or what thing more louely, amiable and beautifull? But out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! great dolour, woe and griefe! There is not any thing more vilipended, nor at leaſt worſe reſpected, nor more baſely reputed, nor more indignely, and opprobriouſly vſed then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6055:24"/>Time is, whereas indeede men are able to gaine and obtain heaps of eternal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in whatſoeuer ſmall portion of Time. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who well know the due value of Time, will not ouerſlip any ſpace or quantity thereof, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo litle without ſome profit, and for which they are to yeeld to God, a moſt ſtrait account. And the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Ber. ſer. ad Schol.</note> That hee reckoned nothing more pretious then Time; but in theſe daies nothing more baſe nor more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible. They let goe the dayes of health, and none conſiders of them, as
<pb facs="tcp:6055:25"/>though by right and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a man ſhould not be greeued to looſe that day which is neuer to returne againe. But let men note, and be aſſured, that <hi>as one haire of the head ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 21.18.</note> much leſſe ſhall anie one moment of Tyme, without rendering good reaſon &amp; account for the ſame. Let none of you (my Bretheren,) eſteeme that Tyme for nought, which you conſume away, and ſpend in idle talke, Words flye away irreuocable, Tyme runnes on irreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diable, and the ignorant doth not vnderſtand what hee looſeth. It is lawfull
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6055:25"/>(ſay ſome) to chat a litle, and to hold conference till one houre be paſt, O! but how long will that houre endure? That very houre, which our Lord hath granted thee to repent, to ſue and proſecute for thy pardon, to purchaſe grace, and to procure glory. O! but how long will that Tyme continue? That ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie time, wherein thou art to procure fauour &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the diuine Pietie, and to make all poſſible ſpeede to accompanie the Angels, to ſigh and deſire feruently for that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during Inheritance; to waken that ſlowe and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme
<pb facs="tcp:6055:26"/>wil, and to bewaile all wicked fellowſhip and impious iniquitie. Thus farre the Diuine <hi>Bernard.</hi> I would to God (ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardine de Sena</hi>) if that traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique and marchandiſe of Time,<note place="margin">Bernardin. tom. vlt. ſer. <hi>13.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.</hi> Et tom. vlt. ſer. <hi>18.</hi> p. <hi>1.</hi> princip.</note> might be caried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell to be ſolde; where for one onely halfe houre, would be giuen a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worldes, if they had them. But Time ſurpaſſeth all things, that are in the worlde, it is ſo gainefull, that men enioying the ſame, may reape and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch grace, as that they may come to poſſeſſe and enioy euen God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, goods &amp; treaſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6055:26"/>And if the Diuell might obtaine to himſelfe but a ſmall ſpace of Time, wherein hee might repent him, then would hee ſaue himſelfe, and recouer that good, which now without remedie he hath loſt. That thing is moſt pretious (ſaith the ſame man) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a ſmall parcell, valueth ſo much as a great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of another thing: And therefore that is the gold, becauſe that with a litle thereof one may buy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and large waights of any other thing or mettal; Conſidering all which, marke well, what a thing <hi>Time</hi> is, and how auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:27"/>in reſpect that in one inſtance of the ſame, if thou knoweſt how to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique wel, thou mayeſt win heauen &amp; life euerlaſting in ſuch ſort as the good Thiefe hath done.</p>
            <p>That holy <hi>Arſenius</hi> wel knewe the eſtimation of Time,<note place="margin">Dion. Carth. in Opuſc.</note> who after he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in ſpending the time, that hee was wont to ſay, That a few houres of ſleep was ſufficient for a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minde. And whereas on a time perceiuing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be ſtung and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered of Time hee called it vnto him, ſaying; Come,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6055:27"/>now come my violent ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, then ſetting himſelfe downe, did ſleepe a litle.</p>
            <p>And if it be lawfull to ſpeake of Gentiles &amp; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men for the confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ill liuers and bad Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of <hi>Marcus Cato cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that three thinges hee greatly abhorred. The firſt was, to repoſe ſecrets in women, The ſecond, To go by water, when one might trauaile by land. And the third was, that hee ſhould ouerpaſſe any day, wherin ſome good were not done. <hi>Plinie</hi> the great, ſeeing one day a Nephew of his, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for pleaſure, ſore chid
<pb facs="tcp:6055:28"/>and reprehended him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, well thou mayeſt doe, not to looſe them houres. <hi>Sertorius</hi> the Proconſull &amp; Capitaine generall of the Romaine Forces,<note place="margin">Plutarch in Sertorio.</note> at ſuch time as hee was forced to redeeme and buy his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for money of certaine barbarous people, ſome of his company murmured, and took that action in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ill part, for that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto them, as Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Romains, he made them this anſwer, I haue neither redeemed nor bought any other thing ſaue onely <hi>Time,</hi> which is a Treaſure moſt pretious of all the beſt and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6055:28"/>richeſt thinges that are in the eyes of the moſt gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt, and moſt couetous perſons that be: To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude then, if the Heathen haue ſo reputed &amp; thought of <hi>Time,</hi> how much more ought a Chriſtian man to eſtimate thereof, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that in and by Time, hee may gaine eternall wealth and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe glory.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:29"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> That we are <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> and to what end <hi>GOD</hi> did bestowe it vpon vs, and wherein wee are to imploy the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE learned and deuout <hi>Laurentius Iuſtinianus</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame which <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> ſaid before,<note place="margin">Laur. Iuſt. de vita ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</note> that all other things are ſtrange vnto vs, but <hi>Time</hi> is properly tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med OVRS, and that wee are <hi>Lords</hi> of the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is in our hands, and lieth in our power, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it as we pleaſe: which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6055:29"/>is no ſmall fauour and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite that GOD doth for vs, in beſtowing as our owne, one ſole thing ſo pretious, and ſpeciallie by graunting it ſo bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſo long, though the longeſt be but verie ſhort; Hereupon ſaith <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> the Time we enioy is no ſmall matter, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon it is, that men do complaine of the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their lyues, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould eſteeme that loſſe to be very great, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they looſe Time. The life is long enough, for perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of ſpecial and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable actions, incaſe the whole be well imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb facs="tcp:6055:30"/>In the Angels, God proceeded ſo determinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and with ſuch limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that for inſtances, hee gaue them ſet termes, and prefixed times for their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, whether they would ſtand or fall; very ſhort ſpaces and moments, as ſom ſay, they were but two or three mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome extendes them more largely to foure, which in truth to them ſufficed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their quick appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, and perfection of their natural inclinations; but to ſlowe, vnconſtant, and changeable man, God hath granted many yeares and ages: Howbeit, not to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6055:30"/>liue idle and ſecure, nor to waſte and conſume it in play, delights, ieſtes, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, meriments, paſtimes, and carnall ſports, much leſſe in ſinne and the hurt of himſelfe, but that it be imployed in good workes, in lawfull exerciſes &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt recreations, &amp; ſhould <hi>labour in the vineyard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 20.2.4.6. &amp;c.</note> and painefully in the ſweat of his browes gaine his daily food and ſtipend, which is the workemans wages, and the reward of his good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture. Whereupon the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.10</note> 
               <hi>Doing of good works, and vſing the</hi> Time <hi>in ſuch things for which it is lent vs.</hi> Let vs therefore, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:6055:31"/>deceiue our ſelues, nor be diſmayed, nor be wearie to reape and mowe <hi>Time,</hi> and we <hi>ſhall gather our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt and fruit in due ſeaſon.</hi> For which, in all that time we enioy, let vs performe what good wee may. And <hi>Seneca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> though an heathen man, ſaith, that <hi>Time</hi> was not ſo liberally &amp; ſo boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully beſtowed vpon vs, that wee ſhould looſe anie part of the ſame, which by the Apoſtle is called <hi>the acceptable time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>and the day of ſaluation.</hi> Wherfore (my good bretheren) imploy the ſame for your ſoules health, to doe workes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and grateful vnto
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6055:31"/>God. And therefore alſo, the time of this life, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Fayre time, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket time. For as in the ſame, wares are ſolde and bought moſt cheape and at a ſmall rate: So in this life, great marchandizes &amp; iewels of infinite value, may be bought at a ſmall rate,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17</note> and <hi>for one momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and light tribulation or affliction may be cauſed an eternall weight of glorie</hi> (as the ſame Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) which in Heauen is to bee poſſeſſed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed.</p>
            <p>And by the way let vs heere note, how by that holy and bleſſed Apoſtle, it
<pb facs="tcp:6055:32"/>is tearmed a waight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that with the weight and greatneſſe thereof, it maketh light and eaſie all the difficulties and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this life, and that which we ſuffer and abide here in the ſame, makes vs to waigh: all which in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is as eaſie and as light to beare, as one ſtraw or chaffe. Euen as a great heauie waight in one end of a paire of ſcales, doth highly lift vp &amp; out-waigh the other end, wherein there is but one ſingle ſtrawe or chaffe: So the waight of our reward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put in the one end of the ballance, doth lift vp
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6055:32"/>the other end wherein our labours and worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are weyed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto agreeth that, which the ſame Apoſtle in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place hath written, namely, <hi>That the paſsions and tribulations of this life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>are neither comparable nor equall to the glorie to come,</hi> which heereafter ſhall be reuealed and manifeſted in vs: till ſuch time by all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, they are very ſmal, light, and of no waight. And vpon that ſimilitude of the Fayors (for appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſake to our preſent purpoſe) it ſeems our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our CHRIST hath meant and vſed it,<note place="margin">Luc. 19.13.</note> when <hi>he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:6055:33"/>the kingdome of Heauen to a man</hi> trafficking &amp; <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing in this worlde;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 13.45.</note> conſidering when he ſpake to all the faithfull (as to men full encombered with many buſineſſes) <hi>Occupie till I come,</hi> for heereafter there will be no place.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the time of this life is called, Time of vacation (from all other buſineſſes) whereby man may ſolly &amp; wholy addict and imploy himſelfe in the ſeruice of our Lord. It is called Time of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to thoſe wordes of our Redeemer, ſpoken by the mouth of his Euangeliſt <hi>S. Iohn, Now is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6055:33"/>the time to worke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>while it is day; the night commeth, when no man can worke.</hi> It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called the time of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, and the time of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and gathering of the Harueſt, becauſe it is the time of grace and faith, wherby the reward of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is to be wonne &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. And therefore by the example of the heede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, diligent, and carefull Emmet, the Holy Ghoſt ſendeth to reproue &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the idle and ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſon,<note place="margin">Prou. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Goe and behold the Emmet</hi> (ſaith hee in the Prouerbs of <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>Shee prepareth her meate in the Sommer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 8.</note> 
               <hi>and gathereth her
<pb facs="tcp:6055:34"/>foode in harueſt:</hi> which ſhee layeth vp and keepeth in her ſtorehouſe or granarie for her prouiſion againſt Winter, which ſeaſon is counted no time to get, but to eate and ſpend that which before was gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and layd vp.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Time</hi> was beſtowed on vs by the Lord (ſaith <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Iustinian</hi>) for to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; bewaile vs of our ſins,<note place="margin">Lau. Iuſtin.</note> to be very penitent, to purchaſe vertues, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in grace, to atchiue faith, to diſcharge vs from helliſh torments, and to obtaine heauenly glorie. And it is ſo true, that Time was giuen vs to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6055:34"/>in good works, as onely that which we ſpend about the ſame, and in vertuous and neceſſarie exerciſes is moſt properly OVRS, and onely entereth within the reckoning of our lyues and account of our dayes: For all the reſt, there is neither reſpect nor memorie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in Heauen, nor in the booke of life; albeit the world makes reckoning of them, records and inrolls them for long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; but our Lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth no ſuch, at leaſt hee ſaith, that hee acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth no ſuch, as a thing which neither pleaſeth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth, nor yet conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:6055:35"/>him, but rather much vexe and ſore offend him. So <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. in Pſal. <hi>37.18.</hi>
               </note> expounding the words of <hi>Dauid, The Lord knoweth the dayes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled,</hi> which are the Iuſt, ſaith thus; In the ſacred Scripture, it is ſaide, That God knoweth but onelie good things, and that he is ignorant of the euill, and them hee forgets; not in that his knowledge can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend all things both good and bad, but in regarde the euill are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie of his ſight &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, <hi>I knowe you not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.12.</note> ſaide he, to the fooliſh Virgines, and as much againe to the workers of iniquitie. <hi>The
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6055:35"/>Lord knoweth the wayes of the iuſt</hi> (ſayed that kinglie Prophet <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4.18.</note>) And <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the Lord knoweth the way of the right hand.</hi> And ſo ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> that the Lord knoweth the houres, and the dayes, and the Time of them that liue without ſpot of ſinne, but is ignorant of the dayes of Sinners. The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes no reckoning of the time of <hi>Sauls</hi> raigne, ſaue onely of <hi>two yeares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.1</note> though hee raigned 40. yeares, becauſe onely two yeares hee liued well, and without blemiſh of ſinne, and the reſidue, were dayes ſtayned and tainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.
<pb facs="tcp:6055:36"/>So of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> Act. 20. verſe 31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dion Caſsius</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">Dion Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</note> that in a Citie of <hi>Italie</hi> was ſound an auncient Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, wherein vpon the Tomb or vpper ſtone ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, were written or ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued theſe words, <hi>Here lieth</hi> Simil, <hi>the Romaine Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, whoſe life, though it were long, yet for all that is reputed to liue, but onely ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares,</hi> becauſe in them hee retired himſelfe from the Court, and being freed of the cares and charge in Office, which formerly was impoſed vpon him, he addicted himſelf to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of vertue, to his owne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6055:36"/>meditations and godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes. <hi>Damaſcen</hi> in his hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of <hi>Barlaam</hi> and <hi>Ioſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> reporteth,<note place="margin">Damaſc. hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Barla. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> that when <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> demanded of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi> of what age hee was of; he made him this aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, (if I be not decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) I am fourty and fiue yeares of age, and ſo many yeares there are, ſince I was borne. What doeſt thou anſwere mee (replied <hi>Ioſaphat</hi>) for thou ſeemeſt to mee, that thou art paſt ſeauentie? I mary (ſayed <hi>Barlaam</hi>) if thou reckoneſt my yeares euer ſince I was borne into this world, thou ſayeſt right, and art not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, for that I am paſt
<pb facs="tcp:6055:37"/>ſeauentie; But thoſe yeares doe by no meanes ſeeme vnto me, yeares of life, nor can ſuch be reckoned in the Account, which were ſpent and conſumed in the vanities of this world; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then (as ſeruant to my ſinnes) I liued after the taſte of my ſenſuality, and appetite of my fleſh and outward man, being then without all doubt dead ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo I may not call them yeares of life, which rather were yeares of death; But after that (by the grace of God) I was crucified and dead to the world, and the world to me, and haue put
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6055:37"/>off the olde man, then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued I no more after my ſenſuality, nor after the fleſh, being enemie to the Spirit, but onely to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and thoſe yeares I call yeares of life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And I beleeue that all thoſe who remaine in ſinne, and obey the diuell, and conſume their lyues in delights and vaine concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences, are departed this life and dead, becauſe that <hi>Sin is the death of the ſoule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.19.21.</note> as affirmeth the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 6.21. Godly S. <hi>Ierome</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the firſt Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Hieron. in Agg. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> All that Time wherein we
<pb facs="tcp:6055:38"/>giue place to Sinne, and ſerue our owne vices, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth and will be loſt, and as though it had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene, ſhall be reputed for nought.</p>
            <p>It is reported of <hi>Titus Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſian,</hi> that being one day at ſupper, and calling to minde, that in that day hee had ſhewed no curteſie nor rewarded any body, nor had performed any good turne, or done any good deede to any perſon, hee ſpake with great feeling &amp; ſorrow of heart, to all them that were then preſent; Oh my friends! how grieuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly ſorie am I, to haue loſt this day; Then let a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6055:38"/>man holde for loſt, that day which by him is ill imployed, and make that reckoning that hee ſhall haue nothing for it.</p>
            <p>For manifeſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this truth, that the yeares ſpent and conſumed in vices and wickedneſſe, are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly OVRS, <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> That there are many who firſt muſt leaue to liue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begin to liue. <hi>Time</hi> (ſayeth that famous Doctor <hi>Thomas de Kempis</hi>) was beſtowed vpon vs,<note place="margin">Tho. de Kemp. <hi>1.</hi> pag. Serm. ad Nouit. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> to performe good works, not for idleneſſe, nor to heare or rehearſe olde tales, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, vanities, nor things of no value. Wherefore my
<pb facs="tcp:6055:39"/>good Sonnes (ſpeaking to the Nouices in Religion) let neither houre nor anie time ouerpaſſe you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome fruit and profit. And when you are freely licenſed to ſpeake, you are not permitted to talke or conferre about any other thing, but what ſhall be commodious, neceſſarie, and profitable. For as you are to giue reckoning to God almighty <hi>for euery idle word:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> ſo are you bound to yeeld a ſtraite account for all the Time which you haue loſt and ill imployed. <hi>Ludouicus Bloſius</hi> amongſt other his exhortations which he giues to ſuch as<note place="margin">Lud. Bloſ.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:6055:39"/>purpoſe to leade a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all life, aduiſeth and ſayth, That he ſhould regard and weigh the eſtimation and value of Time, and eſteem the leaſt part thereof (if ill ſpent) how litle ſoeuer it be, for a very great loſſe. And that myſticall <hi>Thaule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. Thauler.</note> amongſt other docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; admonitions hee giues to religious perſons, ſayth; Take heede and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware (as from the moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiferous poyſon that is) of the leaſt loſſe of <hi>Time;</hi> And ſo one of the Offences, whereof the Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or Chequer-officers; and our Accuſers at the day of Iudgement, ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb facs="tcp:6055:40"/>and taxe vs withall, will be <hi>loſſe of Time,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, which the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations</hi> doth giue vs to vnderſtand,<note place="margin">Lame. 1.21</note> 
               <hi>Vocauit aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum me Tempus.</hi> The Lord called <hi>Time</hi> to be witneſſe againſt mee. The which place <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth of the day of iudgement,<note place="margin">Tho. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin. Sap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are there to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; burthened, one will be <hi>Time;</hi> Where all the whole orbe of the earth (in defence of Gods honour, will commence hard ſuite againſt all ſottiſh &amp; ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſinners, accuſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6055:40"/>&amp; requiring Iuſtice againſt them for the wrong and hurt they did, againſt both their Creator &amp; the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by abuſing and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imploying them, and hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them by the haire, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wills, to ſerue their owne luſts &amp; wicked appetites.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> How <hi>GOD</hi> in his iuſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cutteth off ſinners fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enioying the benefit of <hi>Time,</hi> who before made no reckoning thereof to profit themſelues thereby, as they ought and might haue done.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OTwithſtanding that ſolemne <hi>Oath</hi> of the Angell, (whereof wee ſpake in the firſt chapter) that on ſome day, <hi>Time</hi> ſhould finiſh, &amp; make an end of all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall at the day of vniuerſall Iudgement, after which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6055:41"/>there ſhould be no more Time to deſerue either wel or ill, or to make any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing repentance: And that euery man in particular, in the laſt day of his life is to expect his owne peculiar Iudgement: yet for all that it is greatly to be feared &amp; conſidered. That God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtometh for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the heedleſſe and negligent ſinner, to cut off <hi>Time</hi> from him, &amp; to ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his life, leaſt he ſhould profit himſelfe thereby as he ought and might haue done, conſidering that hee hath ill imployed and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent the ſame. So tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that famous <hi>Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine
<pb facs="tcp:6055:42"/>de Sena,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. <hi>Bern. art.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> and for proofe thereof citeth that place of the Apocalipſe,<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Si non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilaueris, veniam ad te tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam fur. If thou watch not, I wil come on thee as a thiefe; and thou ſhalt not know what houre I wil come vpon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>God</hi> threatneth the careleſſe ſinner, who fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to day deferreth &amp; prolongeth his conuerſion and amendment (dreaming &amp; imagining that he ſhall haue Time enough, yea, to ſpare) ſayeth thus; Be not negligent and careleſſe, neither ieſt nor dally thou with Time, neither eſteem the ſame ſo certaine, ſo ſure, ſo long, nor ſo at thy
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6055:42"/>commaund as thou ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineſt; watch and ſleepe not, be euer warie &amp; well aduiſed; If otherwiſe, hee will come vnto thee as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtometh the thiefe to come, to rob and ſpoile, &amp; will on a ſuddaine, at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, catch &amp; apprehend thee; before thou canſt know or perceiue on what houre he is to come The thiefe comes to ſteale, and to carie away the treaſure, which he ſhall finde heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly layed vp, and which is not kept with that due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and carefulneſſe as behoued; and ſuch is <hi>Time</hi> in the houſe of the ſinner: And therefore with good
<pb facs="tcp:6055:43"/>and iuſt reaſons, will the Lord cut it off, becauſe it was not regarded and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to that end, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by good gaine and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exchange, yea great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, bleſſings, and eternall happineſſe might haue bin had and obtained.</p>
            <p>Conformable to this, ſayeth our Sauiour, by his Euangeliſt S. <hi>Matthew;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.29</note> 
               <hi>He that hath ſhall haue more, and from him that hath not, ſhall be taken away that which hee hath,</hi> or ſeems to haue. The iuſt man apprehends Time as his owne, and is <hi>Lord</hi> thereof, for that hee well knoweth how to vſe it, and to him that hath time at
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6055:43"/>the end of his life, more time and ſpace ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him, to examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe &amp; to purifie his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſhall haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance, becauſe hee ſhal obtaine full remiſſion and compleat pardon of all his ſinnes, plentifull grace, and glory infinite. And hee poſſeſſeth no Time, who (while hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) doth not well imploy the ſame, but being ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and deceiued by the Diuell with prolonging of amendment, thinkes that he ſhall enioy ſufficient, by the iuſt Iudgement of God ſhall be bereaued of his vaine expectation, and ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:6055:44"/>want ſpace to repent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſome ſodain death, or by ſome other diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnfortunate acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; Thus farre <hi>Bernardin Senenſis.</hi> And for that cauſe doth our Lord and Sauiour, admoniſh vs ſo often,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.13.</note> that wee <hi>watch,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we <hi>knowe not the day nor the houre</hi> wherein Time will make an end of vs.</p>
            <p>And the holy Church ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably, like a louing and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionate Mother, doth aduiſe vs the very ſame, ſaying; Let vs reforme and amend that which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we haue moſt ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or wilfully tranſgreſſed, conſidering that no Time
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6055:44"/>of repentance will be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after left vs, which though we ſeeke for, yet ſhall not we obtaine the ſame. And to this purpoſe, as God cuts the thrid of life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time from him, who profited not with Time in his ſeruice.<note place="margin">Bern. de Sena.</note> 
               <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardinus de Sena</hi> reporteth a moſt terrible and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full accident which in his time happened in a certain village of <hi>Catalunna,</hi> neare to the kingdome of <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia.</hi> A young man of the age of eighteene yeares, hauing beene moſt rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; diſobedient towards his Parents, did many times looſe and forget the
<pb facs="tcp:6055:45"/>regard and reſpect due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. In puniſhment whereof, God leauing him to himſelfe, came to be a moſt notorious Thiefe, &amp; for robberies being appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and condemned to die, was brought to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the market place of his owne Towne: And the young man being dead, &amp; hanging vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gallowes, and all the whole Towne preſent, they ſaw and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued his beard to ſprout out, &amp; much haire to grow, &amp; to remaine with a wrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led brow &amp; a writhen face, full of gray haires, &amp; with the aſpect and ſemblance of a man of ninety yeares,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6055:45"/>a thing whereat all were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonied and wonderfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, which accident be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Biſhop, who then reſided in that Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, commanded that all ſhould prepare themſelues to prayer, himſelfe perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ſame, moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeched Almightie God, that he would bee pleaſed, to reueale vnto them the myſterie of ſo rare an accident, and after a pretie while intreated ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and ſpeaking with a loud voyce, ſayd thus; You ſee (my Sonnes) that this young man died of the age of eighteene yeares, who
<pb facs="tcp:6055:46"/>afterwards appeared and ſeemed with the viſage and countenance of a man of ninetie yeares; whereupon you are to note what God would haue vs to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of, namely, that after the courſe of nature he was vndoubtedly to liue ninety yeares, and ſo would haue done, had he beene obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to his Parents, but in regard of his ſins and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, the Lord hath permitted him to die a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death, cutting off from his life ſo many yeares, as are from eighteen to nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And becauſe this might be manifeſt and apparant to al men, he hath wrought
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6055:46"/>this miracle.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Hieron. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> that the ſhortneſſe of life, is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and iudgement againſt ſinners, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe of ſinne the Lord from the beginning of the world, hath ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and cut off the life, and yeares of men. Once God withdrew from <hi>Hezehiah</hi> fifteene yeares of his life,<note place="margin">Iſaiae: 38.1.</note> which according to the courſe of nature, he was to liue, but afterwardes by meanes of his <hi>Teares</hi> and hartie repentance,<note place="margin">Ver. 3.</note> they were reſtored and granted vnto him againe. And ſo <hi>Haymo</hi> vpon thoſe words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Haymo in Iſaian, <hi>38.5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Lord
<pb facs="tcp:6055:47"/>hard thy Prayer, and hath ſeene thy teares, and will adde vnto thy dayes fifteene yeares,</hi> ſaith thus; euen as he ſpake to <hi>Adam,</hi> that he ſhould be immortall, conditionally ſo as he continued obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the diuine precept: ſo by God his eternall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree thoſe years were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to King <hi>Hezechias</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally, if he liued fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and blameleſſe, and would not ſuffer himſelfe to be puft vp with pride: For thoſe yeares which for his pride ſhould haue bene taken from him, nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his humility and lowlineſſe, were reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.<note place="margin">Pſa. 55.23.</note> 
               <hi>Viri ſanguinum &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſi,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6055:47"/>non dimidiabunt dies ſuos,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, The bloudy and deceitfull men ſhall not liue halfe their daies,</hi> That is, as if more plainely he had ſayd, They ſhall not liue the one halfe of the dayes they ſhould haue liued, in caſe they had beene godly. Sinners are not the men whom they think and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine they are; For as our Sauiour ſayd to the Iewes, <hi>Auferetur a vobis regnum Dei, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.43.</note> 
               <hi>The kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you, and ſhall be giuen to a Nation which ſhall bring foorth good fruit,</hi> and ſhall better know how to acknowledge and eſtimate thereof: So will
<pb facs="tcp:6055:48"/>God bereaue ſinners of <hi>Time,</hi> becauſe they yeelde no fruit of good workes in the ſame, and will beſtow it on ſuch as will yeeld good fruite and likewiſe knowe how to imploy the ſame well. Thoſe words of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in his 102. Pſalme, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuoces me in dimidio dierum meorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.24.</note> wherein he beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Lord, that he would not <hi>take him away</hi> out of this life <hi>in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of his dayes;</hi> albeit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſome interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, are as much to ſay, as Oh my God I hartily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee not to take me away in the middeſt of my dayes, becauſe that time
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6055:48"/>and age is the very gulfe &amp; wracke of life, the neſt of cares and pretenſions, and more dangerous to die in, then in olde and decrepit age; and is not ſo ſecure, nor of ſuch confidence and aſſurance: Yet others ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound them to the purpoſe we now treate of, that is to ſay, in other tearmes, O Lord, I feare and tremble that for my demerits and ſinnes, and for hauing ſo ill imployed my <hi>Time,</hi> my life be cut off or ſhortened, which is a puniſhment thou art wont to inflict vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome, who runne on in their wickedneſſe, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the exceeding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb facs="tcp:6055:49"/>finite worth of Time. And therefore do I earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate thee, that I be not vnſeaſonably cut off &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away in the middeſt of my dayes, but that thou ſuffer and permit me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy &amp; fully to accompliſh the reſidue of my yeares, which thou in thy deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination haſt appointed I ſhould liue, if I perſiſted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient in thy ſeruice, as I ought.</p>
            <p>That holy and bleſſed man <hi>Iob</hi> (the mirrour and patterne of all patience) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaith ſpeaking of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man,<note place="margin">Iob. 15.32.</note> 
               <hi>Antequam dies eius impleantur, peribit, &amp;c. Before that hee accompliſh his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6055:49"/>dayes, hee ſhall die,</hi> and his hand ſhall be cut off, as the vine in the bud, that is to ſay, God will take him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and ſhall cut him off in the blade, being young and tender, and ſhall fade and wither away before his time, and in the middeſt of his dayes ſhal be bereaued of his life, as being an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie and vniuſt poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour thereof. Ouer &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides THIS, being a great puniſhment in this life, in the other, the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of <hi>Time</hi> which they enioyed &amp; ſuffered to paſſe away without any profit, ſhall be a great paine and grieuous torment to the
<pb facs="tcp:6055:50"/>condemned ones, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall then though all to late, beholde and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the lack and want of ſo precious a iewell.</p>
            <p>Holy <hi>S. Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. ſer. de fall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentis vitae. <hi>Sap. 2.</hi>
               </note> in a Sermon intituled of the fallacie and deceipt of this preſent life, very elegantly declareth how it bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and deceiueth Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſometimes protra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and making their lyues long &amp; large, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might ſo defer and prolong their conuerſion and amendement in ſuch ſort, as they neuer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards amend indeede or are reclaimed, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times abridging it and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6055:50"/>it ſhort, whereby they may truly ſay, That life is ſhort, &amp; is but a blaſt, and therefore let vs make haſt to glut our ſelues with all maner of delights &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the worlde.</p>
            <p>Wherupon he ſaith, that God amongſt other things cutteth off ſuch perſons in the middeſt of their gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die appetites and licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes for their impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in offending, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both of Time and of their lyues, becauſe ſuch who of their owne accord haue no regard to leaue their wicked wayes, GOD cutteth off before their time, and chargeth
<pb facs="tcp:6055:51"/>them with death, and by force conſtraineth them to forbeare to ſinne any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And for that reſpect many ſinners die verie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouidently &amp; vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie which the worlde iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to happen vnto them by ſome accident, or hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den indiſpoſition, or for ſome manifeſt caſuaſtie; pretending beſides, that thoſe daies wherein they liued not in ſinne, were not true daies, nor the life that they leade, true life, but painted and appearing: Whereupon they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the holy Scripture, <hi>Dead ſinners.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.6. Apoc. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Widdowe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6055:51"/>in pleaſure, is dead while ſhe liueth.</hi> And our Sauiour ſaith in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> vnto a certain Biſhop, who liued not as he ought, <hi>Thou haſt a name that thou liuest,</hi> and the world thinkes no leſſe, <hi>but thou art not liuing but dead,</hi> and for ſuch I repute thee to be, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that thy ſoule remaineth dead within that liuing body of thine; So as the ſinner hath no life in deed, but onely a name that he liueth.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, if that <hi>Time</hi> which the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vainely miſſpend and abuſe, cannot properly be termed a <hi>Time of life,</hi> and that God oftentimes ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth
<pb facs="tcp:6055:52"/>the life and dayes of the wicked; then doe they not, nor ſhall LIVE as the worlde imagineth, but ſhall be very poore &amp; ſparing of dayes, that is, They ſhall die very time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſpeedily; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, vpright and iuſt men ſhall be full of dayes, and ſhall liue farre longer then the world ſuppoſeth; for the Lord will not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them into his barne, vntill it be due ſeaſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:6055:52"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> He that now inioyeth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of <hi>TIME</hi> muſt with great feruencie and zeale labour to imploy it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther well.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F <hi>Time</hi> bee ſuch a precious iewel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon vs to do good workes, and to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the vineyard of our Sauiour all the day long vntill Sunne ſet; And if we profit not our ſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, we may feare and tremble, that it will be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from vs, and that we ſhall want the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:53"/>when we moſt deſire and haue neede thereof: It is good reaſon therefore, that we imploy it well, and that in the meane time with great earneſtnes and zeale we labour in our vocation. So <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> aduiſeth vs, ſaying,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.10</note> 
               <hi>Let thy hand labour</hi> ALL <hi>that it may, and that with earnestneſſe, diligence, feruencie and haſt;</hi> he ſayth <hi>All,</hi> as if he had ſayd, Let no good thought or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination ouerſlippe thee, which thou mayſt obtaine; nor any good word which thou mayeſt heare, Omit not any thing thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to vtter, nor any good worke thou mayeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6055:53"/>forgoing neither occaſion, opportunitie nor time to do good. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſaith, <hi>That which</hi> THY <hi>hand,</hi> and not that which a ſtranger or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans hand doth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou muſt not rely or repoſe thy ſaluation vpon the hands, power or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of any other, neither ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou imagine that thy ſeruant, or thy friend, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other worldly perſon, ought to gaine Heauen for thee, thy ſelfe playing the Trewant, and continuing lazie. Thy hand and thy arme are to performe it, and are to labor with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, earneſtneſſe, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6055:54"/>and zeale, becauſe life flits away, and when thou leaſt ſuſpecteſt, Thy Sun will ſet. Reioyce that thou haſt laboured much, becauſe thy reſt and reward ſhall be ſo much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And the reaſon which <hi>the Preacher</hi> yeeldeth for al aboue ſayd, is, becauſe that after this life no worke ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of reaſon, or of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or any act of will, or of any other power ſhal be of worth nor of profit to gaine thereby grace or glory.</p>
            <p>The ſeuen fertile yeares (prefigured by the <hi>ſeuen fat kine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 41.2.</note> which king <hi>Pharao</hi> ſaw in his dreame) do ſignifie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6055:54"/>the time of this life, which by weekes (whereof euery weeke comprehendeth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen dayes) goeth on with an alternatiue continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; ſucceſſion, wheeling about &amp; proſequuting his path; but afterwards will come other ſeuen yeares (which wilbe al that which ſhall remaine in the other life, which is without end) prefigured by <hi>the ſeauen leane</hi> and hunger-ſtarued <hi>kine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> barren and without fruit of deſert. For which cauſe in imitation of that diſcreet and wiſe man <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 16.16</note> Now (Brother) fill thy granarie and ſtorehouſe, &amp; make prouiſion againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:6055:55"/>time of want and famine, becauſe if thou waite to gather <hi>Manna</hi> for the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth day of the other life, it will profit thee no whit, but rather will be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into wormes; For ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wil remain in thy Soule (whereof we now ſpeake) a perpetuall worme and ſting of conſcience, <hi>Rachel</hi> was moſt faire,<note place="margin">Gen. 30.1.</note> and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aboue meaſure, but <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren</hi> withall, and though <hi>Leah</hi> was not ſo well fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet was ſhe fruitfull. The other life is moſt beautifull and excellent, but is ſayd to be <hi>barren,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no place for repentance &amp; good works,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6055:55"/>proper vnto this preſent life, the which though in compariſon it be browne, duskiſh, foule &amp; laborious, yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding is fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and fertile, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth that ſoueraigntie, which cauſeth and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth works both good and acceptable vnto God, with the encreaſe of grace and aſſured hope of glorie; and he who at firſt doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect theſe things, and with alacritie and patience vnder go his labour and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer griefe and tribulation, and daily buſie himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout good exerciſes, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hope hereafter to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the exceeding and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb facs="tcp:6055:56"/>beautie of <hi>Rachel</hi> the other life.<note place="margin">Matt. 20.7</note>
            </p>
            <p>Then be carefull (thou Chriſtian) to labour and worke heere <hi>All</hi> that thou canſt, becauſe hereafter thou canſt not poſſibly doe it. We are mercenarie workemen and hirelings, and therefore there is no reaſon we ſhould paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our liues idlely, nor in delights, pleaſures and dainties, as though wee were great <hi>Magnificoes</hi> or Gentlemen of high repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Before <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned GOD placed him in the Paradiſe of pleaſure,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.15.</note> the which he ordained for him, that he ſhould labour
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6055:56"/>in that gardeine; that in that lodge or pallace of pleaſure, he ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, ſpend his time and ſolace himſelfe. But after he had ſinned, he was baniſhed out of Paradiſe, and was made a labourer and a workeman of the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall vineyard. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering therefore the caſe ſtandeth thus, labour and make ſpeed (my friend) if thou beeſt deſirous to liue without ſtaine or ſpot of ſinne, and to end thy dayes in all ioy and ſpiritual hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <p>Becauſe this is not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnderſtoode, or rather becauſe few indeauour or
<pb facs="tcp:6055:57"/>care to vnderſtande and conſider the ſame as they ought, men now a dayes conuert this vineyard into gardens &amp; places of mirth and pleaſure, and paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their lyues in all kind of ſenſuality and delight: Who are rightly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto king <hi>Ahaz,</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is written,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 16.</note> that as <hi>hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the Altar of Damaſcus, he ſent</hi> from that Citie <hi>the true patterne and platforme therof vnto</hi> Vriah <hi>the prieſt,</hi> that thereby hee might frame, and make an Altar according to the kings or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and direction; but the Altar of braſſe and of met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,<note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note> which ſtoode till that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6055:57"/>day before the Lord, hee took away out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and from before his preſence, That (I ſay) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Chriſtians now adayes doe practiſe, who embrace Religion, &amp; worſhip God, but vpon the Altar of the Gentiles, liuing as though they were Gentiles or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men, enioying ſo much &amp; ſo many dainties, pleaſant taſtes, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates they can procure and attaine vnto, they fall ſtraightwayes to all ſuch things, as their appetites can wiſh and demaund, &amp; without making of anie maner reſiſtance they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to fulfill and perform
<pb facs="tcp:6055:58"/>what their ſenſualities ſhal long and luſt after.</p>
            <p>Correct and chaſtice (thou Chriſtian man) that body of thine, tame &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due it, buſie thy ſelfe in the workes of a Chriſtian la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer, worke in thy vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, dreſſe and prune it, digge and delue it, plough it, tyll and manure the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of thy ſoule, and thou ſhalt ſee how thy ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality will forgoe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her heady wilfulneſſe, her gallant brauerie and wantonneſſe, &amp; there ſhall not be found in the ſame ſuch ſtore of bryer-buſhes, nor ſo many thornie bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and ſharpe pricking
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6055:58"/>thiſtles of Sinnes as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there ſhould. So, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould not be multiplied,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor recouer any head or ſtrength, but that they ſhould be kept vnder and ſolde, <hi>Pharao</hi> made them worke and labour, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them ordinarie tasks which were not ſmal. Knowe and acknowledge (thou Chriſtian) the good time and the good day, hourd them vp in ſtore, &amp; reſerue them in thy ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, whereby that may not be ſaid of thee, which was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Hebrues. <hi>The Kite, the Storke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaix. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and the Swallow do know their times
<pb facs="tcp:6055:59"/>and ſeaſons,</hi> and well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the due value there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and profit thereby; But <hi>Iſrael</hi> neither knoweth nor regardeth the time of his viſitation, nor vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth how to profit by the occaſion thereof, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall ſome day weepe and lament moſt bitterly, and ſhall much long for, &amp; wiſh euen that which now hee neither eſteemeth nor regardeth.</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the riuer of <hi>Iordan</hi> to be dry, were therefore ſecure in the paſſage, and leaſt they ſhould looſe ſo good an opportunitie, <hi>they made haſt to paſſe ouer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſuae. 4.10</note> and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6055:59"/>indeede paſſed ouer moſt ſafely: But if they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred their iourney till a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother day, peraduenture they ſhould haue come ſhort &amp; found the paſſage ſhut vp. We cannot ſecure to our ſelues the morrow, and if this day thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, deferre it not, let it not ouerpaſſe thee, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert thy ſelfe to God, for it may bee that to morrow thou ſhalt not be able or canſt not.<note place="margin">Pſal. 95 7.</note> 
               <hi>To day</hi> (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>) <hi>if you will heare the voyce of the Lord,</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiteth and calleth you to repentance, and to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, poaſt it not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo <hi>hardening your harts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 8.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6055:60"/>and defer not till another day. Conſider thou miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wretch, thou blinde and ignorant Sinner, that the Diuell to deceiue and delude thee, ſaith, Beſtow vpon mee this day, and the morrow thou ſhalt giue to God, and to morrow hee will reiterate and ſay vnto thee the very ſame, and ſo hee will coſen and vndoe thee.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Baſil. hom. <hi>13</hi> exhort. ad Bapt.</note> That he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a moſt meruailous ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſhift of a certaine litle Bird (which according to <hi>Elianus</hi> is the Partridge) which perceiuing the Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to draw neere towards her neſt where her young
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:6055:60"/>lay, fearing that if hee had come any nearer, he would haue made a pray of them all: wherefore in reſpect they could not well flie, ſhe skipt out of her neaſt and lighted hard by him, putting him in hope, that hee might ſpeedily catch her (hauing her yong ones, as he now imagined ſure in his hands,) of purpoſe to make him to follow her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by-pathes, and whereby he might forget to finde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine her litle young ones. When the Fowler drew neare towardes the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, and thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſure of her, ſhee ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly flurted vp, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted
<pb facs="tcp:6055:61"/>ſom ſhort diſtance before him, and after that maner, alwayes flying and ſtaying, or rather limping and hopping ſtill neare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts him, ſhee deceaued the Fowler by intertaining and withdrawing him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe ſo farre, till at length her young ones by litle &amp; litle with ſhort leapes and eaſie flight, had prouided for themſelues, and digged ſmall holes in the ground, and had hid them all in ſafety. And afterwards, the wylie and cunning dam ſoared aloft, and quite flew her wayes, leauing the Fowler deceiued &amp; aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, conſidering he could
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6055:61"/>lay hold neither of her ſelf, nor vpon any of her young ones. In the ſame maner goeth the Diuell about to delude and entrappe thee (thou blinde and fooliſh Sinner) and ſo detayneth, entertaineth, and draweth thee on, with vaine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and deceiueable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one day to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from one yeare to another, yea many yeares together, with one falſe hope, that hereafter thou ſhalt haue Time ſufficient to repent thee, that if thou neglect it this day, thou mayeſt performe it to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or ſome other day, (as though <hi>the dayes and times</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6055:62"/>were in thine owne hands,<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> which the eternall Father hath reſerued for himſelfe) whereby thus alwaies loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Time,</hi> and the occaſion preſent, thou mighteſt hereafter come to want &amp; lacke all good opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or ſeaſons, then ſhalt thou haue cauſe to bewaile and mone for euer.</p>
            <p>If it be good to conuert our ſelues to God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) let vs do it quickly, let it be done inſtantly;<note place="margin">Aug. ad fraet. in Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</note> wilt thou ſay, I will conuert and turne me to morrow? yea too mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. And wherefore not this day? Conſidering the morrowe is neither ſure,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6055:62"/>nor certaine, Happens there not oftentimes many ſuddaine deaths? Die there not an innumerable mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude without acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging their ſins and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayeſt thou, God help me, what harme haue I ſpoken, by ſaying, that to morrow I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert mee and begin a new reckoning, when of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie it ſhould be done this day? Then God helpe mee likewiſe Brother mine (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) what hurt haue I ſpoken by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it ſhould be done this day? That being much more ſafe and better; and ſo I ſpeak better then thou
<pb facs="tcp:6055:63"/>doeſt, conſidering thou haſt not for thine owne, but onely this day, and yet not all this day, ſaue onely the preſent moments or minutes. How much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were it if it might be, that all thy life were good, for thou wiſheſt and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt that it were amended and reformed, then that ſome part therof be good, though as little as may be? Thou wilt haue, or at leaſt indeuoreſt to obtaine, thy meate, thy wife, thy houſe, thy apparell, thy hoſe and ſhoes, all throughly neate and of the beſt; Eſteeme and reſpect therefore thy Soule in much more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6055:63"/>then thy ſhoes? Thus farre Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The life (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) is diuided into three ſeaſons or times, namely,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> in that that is paſt, preſent, and to come, and of them the Time preſent is the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and that to come is moſt doubtfull, but Time paſt is moſt ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and thereof now <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> it ſelfe hath loſt the dominion and Ruledome, neither is it poſſible, that it can be recalled by anie humane facultie. Then if we ſuffer the Time preſent to ouerpaſſe, we indanger our ſelues to be bereft for
<pb facs="tcp:6055:64"/>euermore without it, but to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. How much more thou ſottiſh Sinner, (Open thine eares &amp; liſten to mee) I ſay, how much more better were it, that in all the Time of this life, yea from the very firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that thou haſt the vſe of Reaſon, thou yeeld forth good fruite, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelfe, and be in a readineſſe againſt ſuch Time, as when the Maiſter &amp; Lord thereof doth come to demaund it, for there is neither mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor houre, wherein hee cannot come and call vs to particular Iudgement, wherein he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6055:64"/>the labourers and workemen of his vineyard, according to euery ones labour and induſtrie. All which out of <hi>S. Ierome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In confirmation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that Parable of the Fig-tree commeth neere this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.19.</note> which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt had planted, &amp; as our Lord drew neare the ſame being hungry and deſirous to eate ſome figs, and finding no figges ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did curſe the ſame.<note place="margin">Mar. 13.28.</note> And the holy Euangeliſt well noteth, that as then it was no time of fruite bearing, And therefore did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict that puniſhment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly vpon the Figge tree,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:65"/>but vpon fruitleſſe &amp; bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren men voyde of good workes, ſignified by the ſame tree. Becauſe that man at all times is bound to yeeld and render fruite, for which cauſe our Lord, when hee comes to ſeeke and findes none, he will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vpon him the paine of his eternall malediction &amp; euerlaſting curſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All things)</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>haue their determined and preciſe times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 3.1.</note> and after that ſort and maner, That all <hi>Time,</hi> is neither opportune nor ſeaſonable for all thinges, for that which is peculiar and naturall for one thing, is not fit for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6055:65"/>buſineſſe, but verie preiudiciall and hurtfull. As if one ſhould ſowe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee ſhould reape, fall and grub vp trees, when time were to plant, To ſpeake, when one ſhould keepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, To laugh, when hee ought to weepe; Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, for man to doe good works, and to labour in the vineyard of our Lord, there is no preciſe nor limitted Time: it is alwayes fitte Time, It will be euer ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, in what houre ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, &amp; in what age ſo euer, admitting that at no time, it be lawfull to ſinne and offend, and that no Time was giuen &amp; beſtowed on
<pb facs="tcp:6055:66"/>man to doe euill or to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute wickedneſſe. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe words of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus 15.20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>God commaunded no man to doe vngodly, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath hee giuen any man licence to ſinne:</hi> but rather aduiſeth and admoniſheth <hi>all men to preſerue and keepe Time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus 4.20.</note> 
               <hi>and that they depart from euill,</hi> becauſe it was lent and giuen them for no other end, but to do good, &amp; to imploy the ſame wel.</p>
            <p>The being of a man idle and careleſſe,<note place="margin">Matth. 20 7</note> as well the workeman as the hireling, is reproued by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the family, yet ſuch an idle ſtanding and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe liuing of him that is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6055:66"/>moſt in yeares, and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged deſerueth and is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of moſt blame. And ſo compareth that royall Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Pſalmes, the Iuſt man,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> with the <hi>Tree that was planted neer the running waters, which yeelded fruite in due time.</hi> By which he meant not to ſay, that as the tree rendreth no fruite, ſaue onely in one moneth, or at one ſpeciall time of the yeare, &amp; not in others: ſo the iuſt man is to yeeld his fruit vpon certain dayes or moneths, or in ſome preciſe and determined yeares, and not in others; But rather ſaith thus, euen
<pb facs="tcp:6055:67"/>as the tree yeelds his fruite in his due time &amp; ſeaſon, &amp; if it did not, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would the owner cut it downe to the very ground: So man ought to render fruite ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his eſtate and profeſſion in his time, And his time is, all the time of his life, And he aduiſeth and warneth him on Gods behalfe, that it behoueth him <hi>alwayes to pray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 18.1.</note> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ceaſe, and to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes watching as it were with a candle in his hand, becauſe he knoweth not <hi>at what houre his Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter will come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 12.40.46.</note> and that he be alwayes prouided in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines with the accounting
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6055:67"/>Booke of Receipts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayments of Charges and Allowances againſt the Time he ſhall <hi>come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund an account of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.19.</note> which were vppon truſt committed vnto his charge and deliuered to be kept, that now they ſhould be reſtored, and of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and profite of the Vineyard which was ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and farmed vnto him, and of his traffique and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. All which is a manifeſt argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ſigne, that at all times the Lord expecteth that man beare fruite, and be prepared as a faithfull and wiſe Seruant. And he calleth his Time,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:68"/>all the time of his life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that after the ſame, (as the <hi>Angell</hi> moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly hath ſworn it) <hi>There ſhould be no more Time.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 10.6.</note> The tree which the Euangeliſt S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Reuelation did ſee, which alwayes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with fruit, and <hi>euery moneth yeelded his owne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 22.2</note> all which was wholeſome and profitable, yea the very leaues therof, repreſent the iuſt man, who alwayes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth fruite at all times and in all the moneths of the yeare, and throughout his whole age, and all that is in him, is good &amp; profitable, as well thoughts, words, as deedes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:6055:68"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> How worthy of reproofe idle perſons are, and who they be.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Seneca de breuitate vitae.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongeſt all men, (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) they onely are deemed idle, who imploy and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict themſelues to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and exerciſe of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit indeed they onely doe liue; ſeeing they doe not onely preſerue and liue out their own yeares and ages, but alſo adde vnto their dayes, the fore-paſſed times of former ages, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:6055:69"/>they haue the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which in thoſe dayes was regiſtred for the behoofe of inſuing poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, whereof they reape great commodity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. Which Idleneſſe (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bin ſo well imployed) is laudable and prayſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, but (excepting this) al other idlenes which properly is idlenes indeed, is moſt worthily to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended: For as the Bird was created to flie,<note place="margin">Iob. 15.</note> ſo was Mán borne to labour. And touching that Idlenes, the ſame <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, that it is the liuing mans ſepulchre, and that the healthful idle perſon, &amp; loyterer that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6055:69"/>nothing but idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred and buried therein, is in great danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into many offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: Wherefore <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccle. 33.26.</note> That I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe hath taught much malice and enuie. A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Schooleman</hi> termeth Idleneſſe,<note place="margin">Fr. Franciſ. in ſua regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</note> the Enemie of the Soule.<note place="margin">Aug ad fra. tres in Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſer. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> writeth, that no friend of idleneſſe ſhall or can be any Citizen in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom.: <hi>8.</hi> in cap. <hi>4.</hi> ad Epheſ.</note> 
               <hi>S. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> affirmeth, that Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is a part of vice, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no part at all, but a moſt wicked peruerſe root, yea the very cauſe and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb facs="tcp:6055:70"/>of all vices, whereof Idleneſſe is the Ringleader and Miſtris.</p>
            <p>That great <hi>Anthonie</hi> with lowde ſhrikes and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lamentation to God almighty, cried out in the wilderneſſe, ſaying, O my God and my Lord, thou true Samaritane and right keeper and protectour of Soules and of bodies, raiſe in me thy grace, afford me ſuch fauour, and beſtowe vpon thy Seruant ſo much mercy, as that thou permit me not to be idle one iote in this Deſert; whereunto in like maner (as the ſtorie reporteth) a voyce from heauen made him this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6055:70"/>
               <hi>Anthony,</hi> thou haſt rightly deſired to pleaſe God. Then pray? &amp; when thou canſt not pray, labor and do ſome handy-work? and alwayes imploy thy ſelfe in ſome one thing or other, performing ſuch thinges, which on thy part are to be performed and done, and then ſhalt thou neuer faile or miſſe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine fauour? It was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the Fathers who liued in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſsian lib. <hi>10.</hi> collat. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> That one onely Diuell tempted a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Monke, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the idle. Howbeit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many thinges are written concerning and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that kinde of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:71"/>my principall intent and chiefe purpoſe is, not to intreat thereof ſo much as of ſpirituall Idleneſſe; Againſt which I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, freeing many of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in that point (who in their owne conceipt and imagination are much oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied) manifeſting and prouing with ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, how they are idle, and how they with-holde <hi>Time</hi> captiuated &amp; impriſoned.</p>
            <p>For which purpoſe I ſay, hee is idle who vſeth not Time conformable to that end, whereto by our Lord it was graunted vnto vs, but rather imployeth it in things vnlawfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6055:71"/>which neither tendeth nor can be directed to his ſeruice, nor to the benefit or profit of his Neighbour, or about ſome other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected or brought to paſſe for any honeſt or laudable end: And ſo all Officers, Labourers, Marchants, Tradeſmen, Workmen, &amp; Hirelings, Kings, Princes, Counſailors, Aduocates, Miniſters &amp; Seruants, and all maner of perſons that are ſuch, doe as it were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and with-holde Time captiuated, when they oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy and buſie themſelues in and about workes, acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:72"/>exerciſes, and ſeruices which are vnlawfull and prohibited by the Lawes, Decrees &amp; Conſtitutions diuine, or not to that end and intent they ought, or elſe doe liue ſo ſecure and retchleſſe, that they do no worke that is good or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God; And therefore (as before wee haue ſpoken) <hi>Time</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on man, not to doe euill, nor to be idle, and he that is ill occupied, is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned and accounted as idle before God.</p>
            <p>In vaine hath he recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a Soule,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.</note> who alwayes offendeth GOD with the ſame. In vaine hath euery
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6055:72"/>Sinner had all that Time, wherein he liued in ſinne; and in vaine haue all thoſe now the ſame, who conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue therein, and for all the time their ſoules haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained idle within them, notwithſtanding that they haue profited as touching the world, and reaped be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereby, and enioy the vſe of their ſtrengthes &amp; powers for other works, actions, exerciſes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices; but as for the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall end whereto GOD graunted the ſame, which was, that they ſhould ſerue him (as acknowledged <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> at length) when hee ſaid:<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> That God created all
<pb facs="tcp:6055:73"/>other thinges of the world for the vſe of humane bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; the body for the fiue ſenſes, and the Senſes for the Soule, and the ſoule to contemplate and loue the diuine Beauty. All the Time they ſpend and waſt ſinfully, or doe not imploy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in thinges about the ſeruice of God, is idle and vaine, And yet for all that you will ſay, that the King is buſie, or a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailour, or ſome Officer or Miniſter, &amp;c. But I will terme ſuch a one an idle Chriſtian, a loyterer or i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle workman in the houſe of God, &amp; millions of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do remaine in hell for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6055:73"/>their idle loytering in that kinde of Idleneſſe, who in their owne imagination thinke themſelues greatly occupied in this world.</p>
            <p>All houres ſpent and conſumed in vnlawfull playes, murmuration, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, in writing &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of laſciuious letters and profane books, which vſually make chaſt mindes diſhoneſt, And thoſe times likewiſe which are ſpent in regiſtring, ſentencing, and iudging of other mens lyues and actions, without deliuering to the partie grieued any Copie of his owne cauſe, and without any mature or full hearing
<pb facs="tcp:6055:74"/>thereof, nor yet well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing it, and before the Iudges haue throughly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, nor as yet haue receiued the Informations they ought, and yet proceede to Iudgement, or acquite by proclamation: Who can leaue ſuch perſons vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for idle ones, who wickedly imploy and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon all good Time. And all thoſe houres which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy ſelfe, or bad, vaine and naughty women haue waſted (which are not a few in number) in decking, trimming, and adorning themſelues, for to enſnare and intangle mens hearts,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6055:74"/>to captiuate Soules and bring them in ſubiection, to make free, and ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty them that are bound. May ſuch (tell me?) be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-paſt, without the ſame cenſure and ſentence? And the time and houres which the ambitious ſort (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are puffed vp, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Ephraim</hi>) doe ſpend and conſume in erecting and building of their lofty Towers &amp; windie Turrets, and in purtraying in the ayre the dreames and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions of their fickle fantaſies, ſpeaking to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, like vnto that proud King <hi>Cyrus</hi> (the type and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of that proud <hi>Lucifer</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:6055:75"/>ſaying, I will ſitte in the mountaine of my teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t northward; I will place my ſeate and my throne ſo high, that my feete may be aboue the ſtarres. What wiſe or diſcreete man will ſay, That ſuch Time is not loſt, miſſpent, and bound (as it were) in fetters and impriſoned? The time and houres which the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous perſon ſpendeth in plodding of his Accounts and Reckonings, imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and compaſſing how and by what meanes, and with what intelligence, he may hourd and receiue ſtil greater gaine, vſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, by way of trucke, or
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6055:75"/>barterie, by changing and exchanging, by vſurie, or without vſurie, adding and extracting with himſelfe, watching, wallowing, and cumbring himſelfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and wholy repoſing all his care, indeauour, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie in his owne reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute appetite, to procure and get all that hee may come to, by lawfull or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull wayes and meanes, either by hook or by crook: requiring good and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Securitie to be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for ſure vndoubted payment and ſatisfaction as well of the principall Summe, as of the intereſt thereof and vſe of <hi>Time,</hi> at
<pb facs="tcp:6055:76"/>the day limitted and prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed; But what man is hee that can ſecure himſelfe, that that day, wherein hee ſhall demaund or expect an Account with conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for Time, ſhal paſſe for currant and good? I neede not diſcourſe anie further hereof, nor mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly expreſſe any more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for by ſo doing, my memorie might faile mee, and I ſhould put my ſelfe to exceſſiue paine &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Wherefore, Is the world ſo ignorant or ſo ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh (being ſo wide and ſo ſpacious) but that hence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vnderſtanding Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6055:76"/>may collect and gather all the reſt, which here may be ſpecified and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if he pleaſe, as well by the Sermons which hee hath heard, the books that hee hath read, and by the holy inſpirations and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enlightening which the Lord hath giuen him, as by that which his owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience (being his owne loyall witnes &amp; faithfulleſt friend, except hee be an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt) hath many times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed and inwardly accuſed himſelfe of?</p>
            <p>And that more credite may be giuen to that I ſay, it will not bee amiſſe for confirmation thereof to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch
<pb facs="tcp:6055:77"/>the authority of the ſacred Scripture, <hi>Dauid</hi> in one of his Pſalmes ſaith of the good and iuſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> 
               <hi>Dies pleni inuenientur in eis,</hi> That in them will be found <hi>full dayes</hi> and not empty. It is a very vſuall ſpeech in the old Teſtament, that they died <hi>full of daies,</hi> as it is ſaid of <hi>Abraham, Iſaak,</hi> and of other Saints and friends of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 25.8. &amp; 35.29. Iob. <hi>vlt.</hi> ver. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt go to thy graue in a full age, as a ricke of corne commeth in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into the barne, Iob.</hi> 5.26. Wherupon if that be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the iuſt, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe may we ſay, that neither the dayes nor years of Sinners are full, but
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6055:77"/>emptie and voyde, yea for number few, leſſened, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed and vain, &amp; their howers, diminiſhed how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and by conſequence will not dye full but empty of dayes.<note place="margin">Dion. Carth. in Iob <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Dionyſius Carthuſianus</hi> expounding thoſe wordes of <hi>Iob. Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vacuos enumeraui mihi,</hi> Emptie moneths &amp; dayes haue I reckoned to my ſelfe, ſaith. That the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner may wel ſay ſo, namely, that he hath wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, ſpent, and conſumed without fruit or profit his time and dayes, and ſo for good workes they were voyd and empty, idle, and full of vanity and all vice,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:78"/>which is as good as right naught. And thereupon <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
               </note> that the life of the iuſt is full, and the dayes of the wicked are voyd &amp; vaine, and naught they apprehend, ſaue only an appearance and ſhewe, much like vnto a greene Reede without either mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſubſtance, or pith. Of the ſame opinion is <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> in his Moralls,<note place="margin">Greg in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. ſup. c. vlt. Iob.</note> treating vpon the laſt Chapter of <hi>Iob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, that all perſons who haue ſo liued, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently do ſo liue, are moſt worthie of reprehenſion, doth already appeare moſt manifeſtly out of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6055:78"/>chapters. Then, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering <hi>Time</hi> to be a moſt precious Iewel, as may well be vnderſtood out of the firſt Chapter, and that it was beſtowed vppon vs, whereby we might win and gaine heauen, by a liuely faith working by loue, as is proued in the ſecond; and that God ſuddenly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtometh to abridge and cut it off from ſuch who do not well and worthily imploy the ſame as they ought, as may bee ſeene written in the third Chapter, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding regard not to accept the aduiſe &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell which by the illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Spirit we
<pb facs="tcp:6055:79"/>haue ſhewed and directed them in the fourth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but beeing altogether forgetfull, and all feare and care being ſet aſide, do by their vnſauorie morſels and bitter taſtes (though out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly guilt and canded) wickedly imploy Time, the which they diſpraiſe and commit outrage againſt, &amp; in ſteed of good dealing or well handling thereof, or profiting themſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, they grieue and vexe it, and do withhold the ſame in priſon and captiuity, without any maner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of what they looſe, or might thereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, nor of what they
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6055:79"/>owe to God, who at his owne coſt ſo redeemed them, and whom, for ſuch and ſo many innumerable reſpects, obligations and rewards they ought to ſerue both day and night, and to loue and reuerence withall their hart and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all their ſoule.</p>
            <p>Such may be compared to Merchantmen, who on Markets and Fayor dayes, not reſpecting the preſent gaine they might there ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, doe occupie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues about childiſh toies, and imbrace fopperies of ieaſts and deceite, and by hearing of Ballad ſingers, or blind folkes rehearſing
<pb facs="tcp:6055:80"/>of old tales and fables, or by ſeeing of ſtage-plaies or Comedies, or other vaine paſtimes at Beare or Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garden; and afterwards do find their purſes emptie, &amp; the occaſions to merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, traffique and to get, to be ouerpaſt. Likewiſe they are like thoſe mariners who comming a ſhore out of their Ship or Galley to prouide them of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their voyage and arriual to their wiſhed port and deſired hauen, doe lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and buſie themſelues in beholding the curioſities which are about the ſtreets and in ſhops, or by walking
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6055:80"/>in curious gardens, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Time</hi> ouerpaſſeth them without perceiuance, and forget themſelues of that they principally came for, and that their Ship, Galley or veſſel, was ready at hand vpon a ſet determined time to launch forth &amp; to ſtrike ſaile, and ſo remaine deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of neceſſaries, poore, comfortleſſe and miſerable in a ſtrange land, becauſe they came too late and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided.</p>
            <p>It may ſeeme to thoſe, who ſo without remorſe or feeling do looſe time, that they poſſeſſe ſo much, that they ſhall haue ſufficient and inough for all things,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:81"/>yea <hi>Time</hi> to ſpare, to repent and amend their liues: Whereas indeed it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth plainely that their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; knowledge do faile them, conſidering <hi>Zeno Cliticus,</hi> being an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man (as <hi>Laertius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) did ſay,<note place="margin">Laert. in vita Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopho.</note> That men had no ſuch lacke or want, nor ſuch penurie of any thing, as they had of <hi>Time:</hi> and truly with good reaſon and ſound probability, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee apprehend not that which is paſt nor that to come, and Time preſent is ſo fleeting, ſucceſſiuely following on, and ſo ſhort, that in one moment it is paſt.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:6055:81"/>
            <p>A certaine deuoute ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man maruailing with himſelfe and bewailing the eſtate of thoſe idle perſons, who ſo fruitleſly without griefe and compunction of hart, permitted <hi>Time</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſſe them, did ſay, The ſlothfull looſeth both this, and the other life, bleſſed is he that ſpendeth his life &amp; his powers in the ſeruice of God. I pray thee tell me? If a well of wine or a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of oyle, were freely giuen thee, which for the ſpace of one whole day ſhould continually runne in thy houſe, wouldeſt thou (being poore) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that one day in play,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:82"/>or rather in looking out Barrels and veſſels where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to ſaue and preſerue the ſame, where by to become rich? Without doubt (if thou wert not mad) thou wouldeſt do the latter: So did that wiſe and diſcreete <hi>Widdow</hi> (of whom mention is made in the ſecond Book of the Kings) by gathering vp and ſauing of the oyle which the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> moſt miraculouſly procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for her to pay the debts of her late husband,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 4,5</note> leaſt the Creditors would take away her two ſonnes for ſlaues, till ſhe had diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that ſhe owed; But out alas! (ſaith that holy man)
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6055:82"/>our blockiſhnes and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſuch, and our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion ſo little, that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God giueth vs <hi>Time,</hi> and the life preſent, whereby in the ſame through his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine grace, manifold bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings &amp; exceeding fauors, we might with that maine and principal ſtocke he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth vpon vs, make our ſelues rich, and ſatisfie that we owe, leaſt hereafter we be made ſlaues to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, without remedy, and without end; yet we lauiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpend and conſume the ſame in vanities and trifles. Agreeable to which, bee theſe wordes of moſt pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end <hi>Iob,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Iob. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Dedit ei lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum
<pb facs="tcp:6055:83"/>poenitentiae,</hi> God gaue man place of repentance and time for the ſame, but hee hath conuerted the good vſe to an abuſe, and in ſinnes of Pride.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:6055:83"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> How the <hi>BODY</hi> detaineth in captiuitie the Time which is properly the <hi>SOVLES,</hi> and how it exalts it ſelfe and rebels againſt the <hi>SOVLE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Body</hi> after the fall, ſo lifted vp it ſelfe, withſtood &amp; rebelled ſo much againſt the <hi>Soule,</hi> as the fleſh (like another bondſlaue <hi>Hagar</hi> towards her Miſtris) hath loſt all awfull reſpect,<note place="margin">Gen. 16.4.5.</note> and would ſeeme to be Lady and Miſtris, and that the <hi>Soule</hi> is but a ſlaue or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:84"/>ſuggeſting that all the Time of this life is only for the <hi>Body,</hi> for his owne gallantneſſe and recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſinfull luſts &amp; greedie appetites; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the <hi>Body</hi> ſheweth great fauour, yea doth a very good turne vnto the poore <hi>Soule</hi> by yeelding it ſo much time as himſelfe pleaſeth; who by reaſon of her deiection for ſinne, was brought vnto this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable thraldome: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhee may ſay vnto God, counting her trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and anguiſhes, that which <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in her great griefes and ſorrowes hath
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6055:84"/>vttered,<note place="margin">Lam. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>Vide Domine &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidera,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold Lord and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how I am become vile,</hi> conſidering that my bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue eſteemeth ſo litle of me, and offereth violence vnto me. And therein doth the Fleſh greatly iniurie the Soule, &amp; with a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger exalteth it ſelfe againſt all reaſon and iuſtice, and is therefore bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore vnto the Soule that which properly is hers, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine leaſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall haue neede of the Soule &amp; Body, both of them doe faile to attaine their finall Saluation.</p>
            <p>For proſecution of this point, there can be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:6055:85"/>doctrine written, then that of <hi>S. Bernard</hi> in his Sermon of the Aduent,<note place="margin">Ber ſer. <hi>6.</hi> de Aduentu Domini.</note> a great part whereof I will here rehearſe. The time of this life (ſayeth hee) is not for the Body, but for the Soule, and for her onely was it aſſigned and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: becauſe the <hi>Soule</hi> is far more worthy then the <hi>Bodie,</hi> and that which firſt fell and tranſgreſſed is firſt to be repaired and remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and therefore becauſe the Soule was firſt in the tranſgreſſion, came the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to incur in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to participate thereof: But incaſe we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be made liuing and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6055:85"/>true members of our head, who is IESVS CHRIST, wee are to manifeſt the ſame, and to conforme our ſelues vnto him, wherein our firſt thought and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt care ſhould be concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Soules, for whoſe behoofe moſt principally HE came into this world, &amp; hath ſuffered the paines and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Croſſe; and therefore let vs reſerue and keepe the care of the Body, againſt that day and time when our Lord ſhall come to reforme it, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>Saluatorem expectamus Dominum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum &amp;c. Wee looke and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect for a Sauiour (who is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6055:86"/>ſafegard and preſeruation dependeth vpon hers. Be therefore ſomewhat curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ciuill and diſcreet, to giue place and preferre ſo honorable a gueſt. Thou art in thy houſe and vpon thy ground, for thou haſt bene earthly, and of earth thou art, but the Soule is lodged in thy houſe and home, as a ſtranger, a pilgrime bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as an exile from her owne dwelling. Tell me (thou Body) what rude, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Clowne or countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, though neuer ſo groſſe or doltiſh block-headed fellow, If a Prince or an Earle ſhould come to lodge in his houſe, would
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6055:86"/>not he with hart and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, retire and withdrawe himſelfe to the worſe part thereof, whereby to ſuffer that Nobleman to enioy the beſt roome or cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? yea, if it were neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, would go and ſleepe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hay or ſtraw, or neer the cinders and aſhes vpon the very hearth, or in the chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney corner. Then likewiſe do thou the ſame, and if it be expedient, leaue off to eate and ſleep for the good of thy Soule, and for the loue thereof looſe thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures, forgo thy paſtimes and ſports, Faſt and keepe Dyet, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhee may bee ſafe and
<pb facs="tcp:6055:87"/>whole, chaſten and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline thy ſelfe, let thy ſelfe bloud to tame and mortifie thy fleſh, if neede ſhall ſo require, that thy Soul may liue; For this <hi>Time</hi> is no time of mirth and ſolace, but of lamentation and teares, no time of reſt and quietneſſe, but of labor and paine; no time of worldly recreations and looſe-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, but of prayer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, nor time of any contentments, but of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations and ſorow. Time may hereafter come of laughter, when thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt reioyce and be mery to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with her, ſo as now thou bewaile and weepe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6055:87"/>with her; For if thou ſowe no tears, thou ſhalt neither reape nor gather any ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie or ioy: Deſpiſe not thy gueſt, eſteeme her not of any ſmal worth or reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, though ſhe ſeemeth vnto thee a Pilgrime and ſtranger, but rather admire to beholde the manifold goodneſſe and vnſpeakable bleſſings that redound vnto thee, as well becauſe of her ſociety and preſence, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by reaſon of her partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation &amp; communicating with thy ſelfe in all things. That gueſt, and that Soule is ſhe, who giueth ſight to thy eyes, hearing to thy eares, words to thy tongue,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:88"/>taſte to thy palate, and to all thy other parts their ſenſe and ſeuerall motions, yea all their grace, comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and beauty.</p>
            <p>But if more cleerly thou deſireſt to vnderſtand this point, then conſider what thou ſhouldeſt bee in caſe ſhe were lacking (I meane) departed or fled out of thy houſe? At that very inſtant, thy tongue would be mute and dumbe, thy eyes blind, thy eares deafe; thy noſe would waxe pale, all thy beauty and comelineſſe would fade and periſh, and then ſhouldeſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine dreadfull and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, foule, filthy, vgly, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6055:88"/>ſtarke and ſtiffe, loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, irkſome and horrible, and wouldeſt bee a moſt ſtinking corrupted rotten carkaſſe, and a dunghill of wormes. Theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wel conſidered, Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeſt thou for one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie and temporall delight &amp; pleaſure greeue and offend ſo noble and profitable a member, ſo principall a gueſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaueſt her of her Time? yea, ſtealeſt and robbeſt her thereof, and conſumeſt the ſame ſo ill, and ſo like a wicked ſcape-thrift. The which falſe deceiuable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes notwithſtanding, thou couldeſt not inioy,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:89"/>incaſe thy ſoule were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from thee? Albeit ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe if ſuch and ſo great glorie and treaſures happen and befall thee by reaſon of her preſence and fellowſhip, though being a Soiourner in a forraine countrey, by reaſon of Sin and Tranſgreſſion, bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of the ſoueraigne Court, and from the ſight of her Lord; Yet what ſhal come and redound to thee, when of all ſides both (Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soule bee reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto the Almighty, and ſo ſhall abſolutely remaine in his grace and fauour, in his friendſhip and inward familiaritie? It is reaſon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6055:89"/>therefore that thou in all patience and meekeneſſe, doeſt diſpoſe and prepare thee to offer thy ſelfe to all things which may in any wiſe profit and ſerue for the obtaining and purchaſing of that reconciliation and amitie, Tell thy gueſt, thy Soule, that which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſayde to King <hi>Pharao</hi> his gentleman Butler or Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer, <hi>I am ſure &amp; certaine that ere it bee long the King will remember himſelfe of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 40.13</note> 
               <hi>and will reſtore thee to thy former eſtate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I prethee, haue me in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance at that time.</hi> So without doubt, ſhe will ſpecially ſtretch her ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:6055:90"/>for thy good and regard thee, if now thou ſerue and vſe her well, and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the time about that which belongeth and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth to the Soule, and not about thine owne onely commodities and peculiar behouffes, on her coſt and charges. And when ſhe ſhall obtaine the grace and fauour of her Lord, and enioy his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſhe will intercede and intreate for thee, and will be thy moſt faithfull friend, and aduocate, and will ſay:</p>
            <p>Moſt mercifull and om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Lord, when for puniſhment of my offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6055:90"/>I was exiled in the worlde, and as a Pilgrime and ſtranger walked there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, a certaine poore, pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and godly boaſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me into his houſe, and dealt with mee moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly, For whom, ſo effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and ſo ſincerely as I may, I moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thy moſt infinite Clemencie and goodnes, that thou requite him, who for the loue of mee gaue away all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vtterly vndoing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for my ſake, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe to performe whatſoeuer I thought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houefull and good, forgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his owne appetites,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:91"/>fanſies, dainties, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, labouring and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, wearying and vexing himſelfe for me, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thirſt, hunger &amp; faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, watching, ſorrowe and tribulation; and for his owne proper neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and peculiar affaires tooke the leaſt part of Time, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as litle as might be, whereby the more might remaine for me.</p>
            <p>Hereupon no doubt wil be fulfilled, that portion of Scripture which ſaith, <hi>Our Lord executeth his will vpon them that feare him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.18.19.</note> 
               <hi>and will heare their prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications;</hi> For when that King of infinite Maieſtie
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6055:91"/>ſhall come, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed with ſhining brightneſſe and glorie, accompanied with thouſand millions of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to raiſe vp and reſtore our bodies, and to reduce them like vnto his owne, awakening the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of that ſleepe, in which now they reſt, by that terrible and dreadfull noyſe of the Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet (thou hauing euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned thy ſelfe towards thy Soule in all thy ſteps and cariage as thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and appertained, Then will our Lord well reward thee with his glory, who will glorifie and cloathe thee, with thoſe moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious indowments of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:92"/>mortality, agility, impaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and brightneſſe, the which in the company of thy Soule thou ſhalt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enioy. Deſire not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (I beſeech thee) to looſe and ouerpaſſe a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſo glorious, ſuch deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, ſuch wealth, &amp; ſuch honour, for any ſhort, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and periſhing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or for any ſeeming good taſtes or carnall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, being indeede full of diſtaſtes and diſlikes. For which moreouer the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are to ſuffer and abide grieuous dolours &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. All which aboue rehearſed out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>S. Bernard.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:6055:92"/>
            <p>Such therefore who for their carnall bodies in this life doe challenge and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Time that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the <hi>Soule,</hi> which they vainely miſſpend ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their owne luſts; neglecting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning, yea and as it were trampling their ſoule vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their feete; the Lord threatneth with great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, in thoſe wordes of holy <hi>Iob,</hi> in the 24 chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 24.20.</note> 
               <hi>Their mirth and pleaſures ſhall moſt ſpeedily end and finiſh, and all their ſweetneſſe ſhall be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wormes and ſtings of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and all mercie and pittie will forget them for
<pb facs="tcp:6055:93"/>euermore, and at laſt ſhall be buried in the perpetuall pit of obliuion, they ſhall paſſe from hard frozen ſno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wie waters, into intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exceſſiue heate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their paines and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and their puniſhments prolonged. The cauſe whereof will be <hi>Pauit enim ſterilem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 21.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Becauſe they fed and pampered the Barren, &amp; they righted not the widowe.</hi> That <hi>Barren</hi> ſignifieth the <hi>Body,</hi> for the more it is cockered, and pampered, the leſſe fruite of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth it yeeld. It is all one, as if they pampered and cheriſhed a dry wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6055:93"/>blocke: The <hi>widdowe</hi> ſignifieth the <hi>Soule,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no widowe ſo mured vp in a corner, nor ſo ſolie left, as her ſelfe is in the houſe of the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, I hartily pray and intreate all Sinners, for the loue of <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> yea all ſuch as bereaue the <hi>Soule</hi> of Time, and aſſume it for the luſtes &amp; appetites of their owne bodies, diligently to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all here before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and then to reforme themſelues, and hartily to repent them for the enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities &amp; wickedneſſe they haue committed; and that
<pb facs="tcp:6055:94"/>they imploy for the good of their Soules all the time they may; conſidering that on her health and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, dependeth all that of their Bodies, and by the welfare of the Soule muſt they come to <hi>abound and be repleniſhed</hi> of that glorie which for euermore they hope to enioy.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:6055:94"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> That lay perſons may lawfully enioy ſome recreations, and intertainments of mirth, ſolace and pleaſure.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe (as holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) our <hi>Fleſh</hi> is neither of braſſe,<note place="margin">Iob. 6.12.</note> nor of ſteele, nor the power and ſtrength therof of hard and ſtrong flint, but brittle, ſenſible, ſoft, feeble, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſuch as will be ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and wearied, yea dulled with labor and paine, with manifold buſineſſes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: and likewiſe for that the <hi>Soule</hi> being vnited, and
<pb facs="tcp:6055:95"/>as it were incorporated with the groſſe <hi>Body;</hi> it is to be granted that at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhee muſt inioy her deſires and ſolace, as alſo the old maried man though neuer ſo wiſe and diſcreet, yeeldeth and vſeth ſome youthfull behauiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his wife, ſpecially if ſhee be a young woman. Wherefore ſome interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of mirth is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and neceſſary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many buſineſſes of care and reſpect for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of the continuall trauell and weariſomneſſe of the body: For if man ſhould alwaies without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion worke and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6055:95"/>he would not onely make dull and wearie his vnderſtanding and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, continually waſt the vigour and ſtrength of his health, but alſo ſhould moſt ſpeedily ſpend and conſume his life withall.</p>
            <p>And ſo whereby gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally both men and bruite beaſts might interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably enioy trauel and eaſe, labour and reſt; Alſo the naturall diſpoſition and condition of ſleepe and of the varietie of Time, it was ordained that the night ſhould ſucceed and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the day, wherein (as <hi>Wiſedome</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 18.14</note>) <hi>All things do keep ſilence,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:6055:96"/>to <hi>Virgil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgilius.</note> All the field as well birds as beaſts are quietly at reſt; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the ordinary reſt was thought too litle, the <hi>Feriae</hi> which we call <hi>Feasts</hi> were ordained, which throughout all Nations, Countries, and people at ſeuerall ſeaſons are vſed &amp; obſerued: It is conuenient and expedient therefore, that after labour there ſhould be reſt, whereby men might repaire their ſtrength, recouer and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a longing deſire and will to returne vnto their labour and buſineſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; without which, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie worke, labour, occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6055:96"/>and exerciſe would be ſo heauie and toyleſome, that our weakeneſſe and feebleneſſe could not be able to beare and ſuſtaine, For as <hi>Ouid</hi> ſaith,</p>
            <q>Quod caret alterna re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie durabile non eſt.<note place="margin">Ouidius.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Nothing can endure or long continue, which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth interchangeable reſt, which according to <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> is the very health and preſeruation of labour.</p>
            <p>It is written of King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſis,</hi> that when his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affaires were fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, hee was wont for a while to recreate himſelfe with his familiar friends. And of <hi>Sceuola,</hi> that vpon
<pb facs="tcp:6055:97"/>vacant houres he played a while at tennis. Howbeit, of our <hi>Sauiour Christ</hi> (ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide the heathens &amp; pagans) it is not written that at any time he laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that he oftentimes wept as at the raiſing vp of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and ouer that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull citie of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 11.35. Luc. 19.41. Heb. 5.7.</note> and vppon the Croſſe: Neuertheles for recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake, when he thought it neceſſarie and expedient, he ſomtimes lead his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples with him to the fields, and ſaid vnto them, Reſt and pauſe ye a while (you that are weake and mortall men) eate your ſelues &amp; refreſh yee, Take
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6055:97"/>breath &amp; recouer ſtrength &amp; ſpirit, whereby you may with more ardent feruour and alacritie of ſpirit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to your ſeuerall offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, miniſteries, and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So that by all which hath beene ſaid in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Chapters, wee are not condemned for all the time that is ſpent in play, recreations, ſports, ſolaces, ſpectacles &amp; ſights which apprehend the ſame ends and cauſes, but rather let vs note and diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that if it be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to keepe order, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and moderation in cauſes of weight and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, much more is it in
<pb facs="tcp:6055:98"/>trifles and friuolous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the which though moſt cunningly handled &amp; framed, yet at times are wont to be diſordered and reduced to ſomwhat; for the perill &amp; danger, which remaineth and ariſeth out of the exceſſe and vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurablenes thereof. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>A Christian man ought to performe and do all things orderly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 40.</note> much more it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth him to preſcribe &amp; limit taskes and meaſure in his recreations,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Tho.</hi> 22. <hi>qu.</hi> 168.</note> and vpon the time which therein he ſhall waſt. And for that reſpect there is a vertue, which is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:6055:98"/>or <hi>Comitas, Genteneſſe</hi> or <hi>good behauiour,</hi> conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to which GOD would, that men ſhould recreate and ſport the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in ſuch ſort,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
               </note> that (as ſaith S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi>) it behoueth not to looſe our grauitie or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie in pleaſure, leaſt the harmonie of good life ſhould be diſſolued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ariſtot.</note> that as a litle ſalt will ſerue to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon one meſſe of meate: So a little recreation ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth life, which recreation is to bee vſed in the ſame manner as ſalt is. And ſo their play, ſports and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainements ought to be lawfull, ſhort, ſeldome, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb facs="tcp:6055:99"/>and not preiudiciall or offenſiue to any, accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date &amp; fitting to the time, place and perſons, &amp; with ſuch moderation and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſſe, as that which he taketh and aſſumeth for helpe and eaſe, be no let or hinderance vnto him, nor any impediment of his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous exerciſes and other iuſt offices or duties.</p>
            <p>That which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and obtained is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and ſtrength, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by things may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter compaſſed and brought to paſſe and effected with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out default or difficultie: For when the faintneſſe of our naturall diſpoſition is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6055:99"/>well refreſhed, it incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and animateth vs to proceed &amp; perſeuere ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; As on the other ſide, it is ſuch an enemy vnto la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and amendment of life, as that our appetite doth couet and long for pleaſures without rule or order, vnleſſe great care &amp; diligent reſpect be had, and that <hi>Mediocritie</hi> bee kept wherein all vertue conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth: Otherwiſe one may fall with great facility into Idleneſſe and vice, and ſo flie from labour, wherupon it falleth out that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man commeth to be diſordered, and for ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie buſineſſes and requiſite
<pb facs="tcp:6055:100"/>occupations to remaine a perſon moſt ſlothfull, idle and lazie, moſt ſlacke and looſe, and leaſt apt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to doe good. For which cauſe the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and the ciuill Lawes haue ordeined ſome docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſet downe limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: Albeit the recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of a Chriſtian, by all good reaſon ought to be much more moderat, more honeſt, and more lawfull, then thoſe which the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, Or the ciuill Lawes do permit or grant.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> tooke a moſt heedfull ſtrait reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Aolian, de varia hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that no perſon ſhould looſe and Time, nor liue
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6055:100"/>idely, nor enter into any matter of ieſt or ſcoffe, ſaue onely in laudable workes, honeſt labours and vertuous exerciſes; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as vpon a day it came to the notice and knowledge of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Magiſtrates, that the Inhabitants of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,</hi> were gone foorth to walke at noone time: they ſent after them a letter to this effect, Walke ye not abroade ſo much for mirth and recreation ſake, as for the exerciſing of your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, becauſe it is very fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; behoouefull for the <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> to ſeeke out help &amp; remedy for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of their healths,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:101"/>not by walking and loyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but with bodily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, about things lawfull and profitable.</p>
            <p>Some ſports there bee which are good &amp; lawfull, and occaſion may be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; opportunitie ſerue, wherein paſtime may be a vertue, as then chiefely when it is neceſſarie for man for the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and performance of his office and function,<note place="margin">S. Tho. <hi>22.</hi> Qu. <hi>168.</hi>
               </note> ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally being vertuous, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſeruice of our Lord, for the obtaining of greater ability &amp; ſtrength for fulfilling thereof, That therby he may make due ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for the ſame, leaſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6055:101"/>otherwiſe he ſhold faile, or be diſmayed in the high co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon pathway, &amp; as the Spaniſh Prouerb ſaith, <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no dar con lacarga en el ſuelo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Spaniſh Prouerb.</note> leaſt our burthen &amp; charge fall in the mire, and ſo wee might looſe our labour. Which by litle and litle with great moderation and ſobriety are to be vſed, and with ſuch diſcretion and heedfulnes (as concerning the end and intention) they were firſt inuented, &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after their greedie appetites for lucre &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit haue croſſed them in ſome playes, which I holde more then hurtfull and damnable; which not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:6055:102"/>are no helpe or ayde for the furthering of our offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſpeciall duties, which on Gods behalfe &amp; our owne conſciences we are bound to effect, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and impediment &amp; let, yea an occaſion whereby we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit therein no ſmall defects; but oftentimes many offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces againſt God, as lying, ſwearing, falſe oathes, frettings, contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſtanding moſt ſtifly &amp; ſtoutly in bad quarels, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing and earneſt labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in ſtrifes, which are wont to cauſe diſlikings, euill words, enmities, and rancour, wherefore I holde and am of opinion that the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6055:102"/>Time which is ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſuch playes &amp; ſports, for ill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and loſt, for capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated &amp; impr ſoned Time.</p>
            <p>It is very neceſſarie that perſons go viſite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with <hi>Charitie,</hi> which is a recreation moſt lawfull for the continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; preſeruation of ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and friendſhip.</p>
            <p>Conformable to which, a certain Philoſopher ſaid, That Taciturnitie or Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, hath vndone manie friendſhips, or broken ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie a louing knot: But the imparting to their friends of their contentments in their actions, labours, and chaunces for the greater
<pb facs="tcp:6055:103"/>ioy of the one, &amp; the hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe and comfort of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a thing moſt lawfull and laudable, &amp; the Time needful &amp; expedient about the ſame, is well imployed; Howbeit, many of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings &amp; goſſippings which now adayes are vſed, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo prolix &amp; tedious, ſo without fruite or profit: Or ſo hurtfull and preiudiciall to themſelues and to their Neighbours, or all that they treate of it but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſauoureth of the world and her faſhion; ſo as I hold ſuch for perillous and dangerous, and the time therein ſpent, for ill imployed &amp; captiuated.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:6055:103"/>
            <p>And I beleeue it is the Tongue which conſumeth &amp; vnthriftily ſpendeth the moſt Time, becauſe that kinde of Tattle or prittle prattle will neuer ceaſe &amp; haue end, or be wearied &amp; tired, and the fire thereof is it, which moſt prolongeth and longeſt putteth off &amp; deferreth repentance, and her ſpots &amp; blemiſhes are they that moſt ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and furtheſt creepe, &amp; ſhe is that moath which deuoureth and deſtroyeth the moſt cloathes, yea that which with her fine cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and queint ſubtilty, will neither remit nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:104"/>
            <p>The feaſts and banquets which are made for conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of peace, loue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, amitie and vnity, or for any other iuſt cauſes are lawfull, being vſed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued with that tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and moderation as appertaineth &amp; with their due circumſtances, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth Chriſtians. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe for the moſt part as they are nowe vſed with ſuch diſorders, ryot &amp; exceſſe, for ſo many houres and for ſo long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I may not be bold nor dare preſume to make them good and perfect, nor to vndertake their iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon my conſcience,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6055:104"/>becauſe the moſt part of Time which therein they waſt and conſume, I rather hold as ill imployed and impriſoned.</p>
            <p>Concerning meriments, leapings and dauncings, I haue nothing to ſay, ſauing that I thinke many of them to be moſt laſciuious and wanton, and that many times they wake and ſtirre vp them that ſleepe, and do change and alter the ſpirits and affections of chaſt ſoules and honeſt harts, and do diſquiet men, raiſe an hurly burly, cauſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vnlawfull and vnmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thoughts and diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red deſires and luſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:6055:105"/>I hold much of that time, which therein alſo is conſumed and ſpent, for ill imployed and captiuated.</p>
            <p>And whereby it may be ſeene, with what modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtint men ought to vſe their recreations and ſports. It will not be out of purpoſe or in vaine for the ſhortning and abridging of the ſuperfluitie of worldly contentments; to write that which diuine <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> rehearſeth in reproofe of thoſe words which they call <hi>Donayres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoft. in expoſ. Epiſt. ad Epheſ. ſer. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Merrie ieſts, wittie ſayings, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings, fooliſh tales, or taunts to make people laugh, counterfeiting of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6055:105"/>mens geſtures, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fings, making of mowes, dancing the Antique, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ridiculous toy to moue fond delight, legerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, iuggling, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of apiſh comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to vſe termes ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſharpe biting &amp; taunting toungs, and which are mingled with malice; for the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences which thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doe inſue, <hi>ſayth:</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, this life and the time thereof, is the Time of warre, of watching, and alwayes to go ready with armor on our ſhoulders, &amp; our eyes ſtaring againſt the plots and ambuſhments of
<pb facs="tcp:6055:106"/>the enemies, and by good reaſon, <hi>Time</hi> hath here no place of laughter, which is carnall and of the Sonnes of the world, who profeſſe and obſerue the lawes, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and abuſes of the ſame. Heare (thou Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian) our Sauiour Chriſt, ſpeaking to al <hi>His, The world ſhall ſport it ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall laugh and be merrie, but you ſhall weepe and walke ſadly and penſiuely:</hi> Chriſt was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and buffetted for thy Sins, and thou deſireſt to paſſe this life in <hi>Donayres, &amp;c.</hi> Merry Ieſts, fond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, mirth, laughter and vaine paſtimes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:6055:106"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> That likewiſe it is lawfull, yea very neceſſary for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Eccleſiaſticall perſons to vſe ſome honeſt exerciſe, which may ſerue for intermiſsion, recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Heretickes,<note place="margin">Alph. de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro aduerſ. haereſ. lib. <hi>11.</hi> verbe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio.</note> who miſinterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe words of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt <hi>S. Luke,</hi> where it is ſayd that men <hi>ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to pray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 18.1.</note> 
               <hi>and neuer to waxe faint;</hi> brought into the Church that falſe and new coyned doctrine, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:6055:107"/>that no other thing was to be done and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med neither night nor day, but <hi>onely to pray,</hi> and that without any manner of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion, interruption or ceaſing howſoeuer: For man ought onely to bee occupied and imployed therein: But theſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes were ſithence not without great reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and baniſhed out of the Church, becauſe it was not poſſible that our weakneſſe and feebleneſſe ſhould endure and be able alwayes to pray, in ſuch ſort as they haue affirmed; Neither are the words of the Euangeliſt ſo to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6055:107"/>and expounded, neither hath the infallible Veritie ſpoken them in that ſenſe.</p>
            <p>That which by theſe wordes,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>It is expedient al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to pray,</hi> and by thoſe of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Salmeron.</note> 
               <hi>Pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually</hi> without ceaſing, is meant, is this; when as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie compelleth vs to aske any thing of God, or when we are driuen to any ſtraitneſſe, tribulation or aduerſitie, or doe feare any ſuch thing, then are wee to entreate and beſeech with earneſtneſſe and perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, once, twiſe, &amp; thriſe, till hee ſhew mercy vpon vs, reward, aſſiſt, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:6055:108"/>vs without faile or fraud, not ceaſing nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſmayed, though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently hee doe not ſenſibly beſtow or grant that which we demaund, but that wee knock and call at the gate of his bountiful mercy, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be opened for vs, and that if he pleaſe, he beſtow vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs our deſires, becauſe of our importunacie, euen as the Lord in the Parable of the widdowe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Iudge doth teach vs the ſame (which then to that purpoſe he propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded after he had ſaid,<note place="margin">Luc. 18.2. <hi>&amp; ſeqq.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Men ought alwayes to pray,</hi> who with meere importunacie and perſeuerance, came to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6055:108"/>wearie the Iudge for the grace and fauour ſhe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And this is confirmed by the example of the Church who prayed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion, for the Apoſtle <hi>S. Peter</hi> while hee was detained in priſon,<note place="margin">Act. 12.5.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he was deliuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and that ſhe ſaw him ſafe.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, that ſaying, <hi>Pray continually,</hi> is as much to ſay, as Pray at houres &amp; time conuenient, wherfore <hi>Dionyſius Carthuſianus</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſ.</note> Let him that prayeth, pray without intermiſſion in due times; and he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alwaies, who prayeth when he may, and hath oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and fit opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:6055:109"/>thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon de Caſsia</hi> declareth it thus;<note place="margin">Simon de Caſſ. in Iob. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> All the life of man is a continuall triall and warfare, and all the time he continueth and abideth here, our enemies wage battell againſt vs both night &amp; day without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or intermiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And of our ſelues or by our owne proper ſtrength and might wee are not able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quer them, nor to withſtand their force, and therefore it behoueth vs to <hi>pray continually,</hi> and to entreate for aide and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of that LORD, who onely is able to graunt our requeſts, for which cauſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6055:109"/>the Spaniard ſaith, <hi>En todas maner as es oportuna la ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion importuna:</hi> that is, By all meanes an importunate prayer is alwaies oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and fitting: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not to be ſo inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that there muſt be no ceaſing nor intermiſſion of any <hi>Time</hi> in prayer, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that our ſleepe, our eating and drinking do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten conſtraine vs, as alſo our apparrelling, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we muſt reſt and eaſe our ſelues, and men muſt haue time to prepare them ſelues to their ſeuerall offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and miniſteries, &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to recreate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire themſelues for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb facs="tcp:6055:110"/>of corporall and ſpirituall works of mercie: but that which is ſought &amp; expected of vs is, that our intention be wholy ſetled towards God, and that all our workes be onely dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and intended to his glory, &amp; that at times and houres conuenient, our hearts and thoughts be lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp vnto him, to pray &amp; begge that which we lacke and haue need of, So as all our life time, it behooueth to <hi>pray continually,</hi> becauſe throughout the whole courſe thereof, there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day nor houre, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in man may ſay, that there is no neede, or can leaue
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6055:110"/>vndone ſo neceſſarie, and ſo important an exerciſe. But euer and alwayes to continue in prayer &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation: there is no head can beare it, nor body en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it, nor any Lawe of God that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth any ſuch thing, nor obligeth or bindeth vs to anie ſuch taske, (becauſe his <hi>yoke is eaſie &amp; pleaſant, and his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then light</hi>) and there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges wherein wee ought to be imployed, which charitie and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie demaund and require at our hands.</p>
            <p>And for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all things, how ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or holy ſoeuer a man
<pb facs="tcp:6055:111"/>be, it is very needfull and requiſite that he haue and exerciſe ſome lawfull oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation and honeſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, or ſome other functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which may ſerue him for recreation and eaſe to lighten the heart, becauſe that variety (as ſaith <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doretus</hi>) takes away the irkeſomneſſe and loathing,<note place="margin">Theodor. li. de prouid.</note> and cauſeth freſh deſires and new appetite to ſpring and grow in vs, and ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards man will returne with better liking &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abilitie, &amp; with a more feruent deſire and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his ſpirituall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. Wherefore,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 3.</note> euen as the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> in that his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet<note place="margin">Salomon,</note>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:6055:111"/>iudgement and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,<note place="margin">1. King 3.25.</note> which hee gaue for ſatisfaction of the two wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who ſued for the child, each of them affirming that it was hers, where he commanded that it ſhould be diuided &amp; parted in the middeſt, and ſo diſtributed betwixt them both: So the wiſe, prudent, ſpiritual ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is to part and diuide his <hi>Time</hi> betweene the Soule and Body, yeelding &amp; ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring to either of them the part due to the ſame: And as true husband <hi>Iacob</hi> with his two wiues <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ 29.23. ver. 30.</note> was wont by turnes to exerciſe himſelf in both lyues; namely, actiue and
<pb facs="tcp:6055:112"/>contemplatiue, giuing the moſt he could, to the moſt perfect and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</p>
            <p>And becauſe that in this miſerable and wretched life, the ſoule is not able to attend alwayes on ſpiritual things, therfore all authors that write of ſpirituall life, ſay, that ſome interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Time is very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, whereby the ſpirituall man might exerciſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſome honeſt and lawfull trade or occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhould neither withdrawe nor auert the ſoule, nor reſtraine the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but ſuch as ſhould ſtrengthen and comfort
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6055:112"/>them, and ſerue for ayd and courage. For which cauſe thoſe Fathers who in time of perſecution liued in the Deſart and ſolitary places, enioyed and vſed their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall occupations, or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily trauels, and ſet times thereto limited and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, whereby the Diuell might alwayes finde them occupied either in corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or ſpirituall exerciſes, which corporall exerciſes ſerued in ſteede of recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and repaſt, and for the obtaining of more valour and courage, to performe the ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>So ſaith <hi>S. Ierome</hi> in his Rule,<note place="margin">D. Hiero. in reg. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> Giue no place nor
<pb facs="tcp:6055:113"/>entertainment to idle and wandering thoughts, for if they begin to be Lords o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thee, &amp; to maiſter thee, thou ſhalt perceiue and feele in thy ſoule a moſt heauy loſſe and great dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. And leaſt the Diuell doe finde thee lazie &amp; idle, procure (when thou doſt not contemplate) to doe and execute ſome handie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, as by making ſome baskets of ruſhes, or by fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming &amp; compoſing ſome ſmall fruite diſh or platter of ſlender, fine, delicate twigs or oſyars: Digge a while in ſome garden, and the ground being ſeaſoned and prepared, dreſſe and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6055:113"/>make euen the ſame, frame it in order, meaſure it with a line, and diuide it into ſquares &amp; make beds, ſowe and ſet therin diuerſe ſorts of pulſe, plants, ſeedes and flowers. Viſite them often, ſuccour and prune them, &amp; in due time water them, and as the ſeeds are grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſprouting, rake and pluck vp the wilde hearbs and noxious weeds; and if it pleaſe thee, thou mayeſt graffe ſome trees, whereof thou mayeſt in time come to gather their ſauorie and wiſhed fruite. Make hiues, whereinto the induſtrious Bees may retire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues and abide, and worke their
<pb facs="tcp:6055:114"/>ſweet hony combes: we aue and make nets to fiſhe and catch the buſy rouing fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; Write and compound bookes; pourtray &amp; drawe pictures, Paint or limme them with collours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the idle is an ocean of thoughts,</hi> and therefore the religious men of <hi>Aegypt</hi> doe accuſtome to receiue none that is ignorant of ſome office or ſcience, not ſo much for the earning of his victuals, as for that which imports the ſoules health, and for the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of idlenes, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by with the varietie and change of exerciſes, hee might returne with more
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6055:114"/>earneſtneſſe and deſire to the ſpirituall exerciſe of prayer and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation, the which in this preſent life none can poſſibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure continuallie. And moreouer, writing to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrias,</hi> hee ſaith:<note place="margin">Idem epiſt. ad Demetr.</note> It is of great importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie that thou looſe no time, but remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt alwayes occupied, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chiefly at the houres of <hi>Pryme,</hi> the <hi>third, ſixt,</hi> and <hi>ninth</hi> houre, at <hi>Euenſong, Completorie,</hi> and <hi>Morning prayer,</hi> wherein euery day thou art to exerciſe thy ſelf in prayer, aſſigne to thy ſelf appointed houres for ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, to learne and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſacred Scriptures,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:115"/>and after thou haſt ſpent ſome time there-abouts, &amp; perceiueſt the thoughts, and care of thy Soule, to haue awakened, ſtirred, and moued thee, to fall downe vpon thy knees, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to kneele vpon the bare ground, haue due reſpect to the ouer-plus of time, hauing alwayes ſome buſineſſe &amp; work at hand, and doe thou ſpinne the wooll, bumbaſt, or cotton, flax, hempe or towe which remaineth on thy Diſtaffe, or reele and winde vp bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of yarne, ſtitch and ſowe a while, labour and performe ſome ſuch like worke, for if thou be buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6055:115"/>the dayes will neuer ſee me long or tedious, but eaſie and ſhort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. Berm, tract. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſolitar.</note>And diuine <hi>S. Bernard</hi> in his Treatiſe of ſolitarie life counſelleth the ſame, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: After thy daylie ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of prayers, after thou haſt ſtudied thy leſſon, and after the examination of thy conſcience, vſe &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſome occupation or bodily exerciſe, whereby the ſoule &amp; ſpirit may for ſome ſhort time reſt &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh it ſelfe, yea pauſe and breath, leaſt thou be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, auerted, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from thy purpoſe of godly exerciſe, from the which when thou pleaſe or
<pb facs="tcp:6055:116"/>ſeeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt depart and leaue of, or be freely diſpatched with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any maner of offence or diſpleaſure. For as man was not created for the woman,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> but the woman for the man: So, the bodily exerciſe ought to be for the ſpirituall, and to helpe and further it, but not to hinder or diſturbe the ſame by no meanes. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as the Companion, which God gaue to <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 23.</note> was in all reſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce moſt like vnto him, made and formed of his rib, bone, and fleſh; So likewiſe the helpe, aſſiſtance and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, which ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:6055:116"/>and beare fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the life ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, muſt reſemble and holde proportion with things ſpirituall, and by reaſon of their affinitie, either of them ſhould bee the badge and token of the other, as to meditate ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what that hath beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or written, or to write ought that was read or heard; for if they were la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious workes of great paines and wearines, ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and as it were diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the ſenſes, and tyring the body, the ſpirite and courage of well dooing would bee altogether aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaged and abated, and
<pb facs="tcp:6055:117"/>the deuotion leſſened and diminiſhed, yea made luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme. Therefore the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and ſpirituall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt take heede of, and looke diligently, that the <hi>Time</hi> bee not ouermuch which he ſhall ſpend in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily exerciſes, but ſo as with great eaſe and facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he may returne againe to his ſpirituall deuotion; howbeit the while and ſpace that the corporall endureth, he ought not to bee alone and his exerciſe careleſly performed, but accompanied with others, and refreſhed with the ſpirituall. Corporall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, are thoſe which are
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6055:117"/>tearmed handycrafts or workes of the bodie; for otherwiſe watchings, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſuch exerciſes of mortification, doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not perturbe or hinder, nor cauſe any hurt or da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the ſpirit, and are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto the ſame, but rather they are moſt fauourable and profitable, if they be done and ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with diſcretion and wiſedome as is requiſite. And the ſame <hi>Saint Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> writing of a religious Siſter of his,<note place="margin">Idem tract. forma bene viuendi ad ſoror. ca. <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> ſaith thus; Thou (ſeruant of God) muſt alwaies read, pray, and labour, that the ſpirit of diſhoneſtie beguile not
<pb facs="tcp:6055:118"/>thy idle ſpirit, and carnall delights, and fleſhly luſtes haue the vpper hand of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and paines-taking. Diuide the day (Siſter) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts, in the firſt, <hi>pray?</hi> in the ſecond, <hi>read?</hi> and in the third, <hi>labour?</hi> and performe ſome handie worke: Prayer, doth purifie and make vs cleane, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, doth teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs, and labour makes vs bleſſed and happy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of <hi>Dauid; Thou ſhalt be happy and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 128.2.</note> 
               <hi>and all things ſhall happen well vnto thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou eateſt the fruit of thy handiworke and labours.</hi> And who ſo well and ſo
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6055:118"/>wiſely parteth and ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Time</hi> in this maner, ſhall haue no recconing to yeld vnto God Almightie of <hi>Time</hi> ill imployed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall <hi>Time</hi> haue whereof to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:6055:119"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> How <hi>TIME</hi> is to bee redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and who they be that detaine the ſame in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul,</hi> amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther documents, exhortations and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes that hee gaue to the Cittizens of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and to all Chriſtian people, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee had admoniſhed them, that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware from ryotouſnes and couetouſnes, and from all other workes of darkenes,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6055:119"/>and that they ſhould not communicate with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes being enemies of the light, ſaith thus;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.15</note> 
               <hi>Videte quomodo cautè ambuletis &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you ſee how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daingers there be, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, impediments, lets, &amp; ambuſhments in the way to heauen, and how many theeues and robbers, py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, rouers and other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies hinder the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; therefore <hi>Looke about you and bee aduiſed how you walke,</hi> and how you trauel that way, make your iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney warily, with ſpeciall care and heedfulnes, with much vigilancie and feare, leaſt you fall into their
<pb facs="tcp:6055:120"/>ſnares. <hi>Walke not as fooles, but as wiſe,</hi> diſcreet, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, circumſpect and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, leaſt by following and proſecuting the enemies plots and practiſes you be quite ouerthrowne. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that it is ſayd,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>Redimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus tempus &amp;c. Redeeme the time becauſe the dayes are euill.</hi> The firſt expoſition or explanation of which wordes (becauſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part thereof is trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Chapter ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent) is of <hi>Saint Ierome</hi> where he ſaith,<note place="margin">Viegas in Apoc. cap. <hi>10.</hi> citat Hieronym.</note> that God beſtowed <hi>Time</hi> vpon men wherby he might be ſerued in it, and they occupied in good workes, (the which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6055:120"/>more at large may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in the ſecond chapter precedent) which notwithſtanding they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as captiuated and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, imploying the ſame in bad workes &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed affaires (which is a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie moſt culpable and blameable, and moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be lamented) But <hi>Time</hi> is to be redeemed and ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſomed, by doing of good works; for then doth man redeeme and buy it, and make that properly his owne, which malice had detained as ouercome and alienated.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Expoſition is this, God cutteth ſhort
<pb facs="tcp:6055:121"/>&amp; diminiſheth many times from Sinners their dayes and time, the which by the courſe of nature (had they beene good) ſhould haue liued lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, (as in the third chapter before wee are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed) Wherefore the good, iuſt, and vertuous man, and hee that imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his time well, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme &amp; ranſome it. Then hee that reſcueth and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſometh that part of time and ſpace of life, wherein he liued ſinfully, for which God by his iuſt Iudgement would haue cut him off, ſhal now enioy all the time that Nature had aſſigned and appointed him to liue
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6055:121"/>in, and ſhall die a good v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer or great gayner of time, &amp; full of dayes.</p>
            <p>The third Expoſition is, That hee redeemeth Time who taketh part thereof from the affaires and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique of the worlde to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe it in the ſeruice of God, for the enioying of the inward peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes of his Soule, for the idleneſſe of <hi>Marie Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> is not to be accounted Idlenes,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.39</note> but holie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious imployment.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, he that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Time with ſuch circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect limitation and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſpect in his tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie commodities and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb facs="tcp:6055:122"/>buſineſſes, as that he doth not imploy the whole day therein, but now and then borrowes a litle from his worldly imployments, and ſaues &amp; reſerues it for the Soule, for her beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage and greater bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; hee is truly ſayed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme and purchaſe <hi>Time,</hi> and to beſtow for the ſame euen that which he ſaued and ſpared from his world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaires for his Soules health. And albeit this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption &amp; ranſome (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the delight and good liking otherwiſe of the which hee is depriued) aggrieueth him in ſuch fort, as it ſhould grieue one
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:6055:122"/>to be beguiled of his din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who had a good appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite thereunto, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding man ought very earneſtly and eagerly to ſtriue and procure by all meanes to redeeme and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer againe the pawne or pledge of a thing ſo preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as <hi>Time</hi> is, conſidering that paſtimes &amp; ſports, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and exceſſiue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments and recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, were the money and price by the which it was ſolde to the Diuell, who beguiled vs moſt notably in the ſale thereof, with his great ſubtilty and forcible enticements as well of the Time it ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb facs="tcp:6055:123"/>woorth and value thereof.</p>
            <p>Agreeable to which, that moſt famous Doctor of the Church <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ſer. <hi>24.</hi> de verb. Apoſtol.</note> 
               <hi>To redeeme Time</hi> is, as when any body implea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or ſueth thee for thy goods, to looſe ſomewhat thereof for the gayning of Time to ſerue and pleaſe God, and to abſtract there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as by ſuits of law thou ſhouldeſt ſpend; &amp; that which thou ſeemeſt to looſe, thou gaineſt, which is the price where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou haſt bought Time; and ſomething muſt be loſt to get, and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe; for if thou goeſt to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6055:123"/>the market place to buy bread, wine, or oyle, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther merchandice; thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt &amp; receiueſt, thou lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt &amp; receiueſt, thou lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt behind one thing, and bringeſt home another, thou leaueſt money behind thee which thou looſeſt, &amp; carieſt home thy ware or merchandiſe, and that is to buy: for if thou haddeſt not giuen ſomething, thou ſhouldeſt not haue now wanted what thou hadſt, but thou ſhouldeſt haue poſſeſſed much more then before, if haply thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt found it, or diddeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite it, or elſe that others in curteſie had beſtowed the ſame vpon thee; but
<pb facs="tcp:6055:124"/>when thou giueſt and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, or takeſt out of thy houſe one thing to bring home another, then doſt thou buy &amp; purchaſe: and that which thou inioyeſt, is that which thou bough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, &amp; that which thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweſt and haſt not, is the price wherewith thou haſt bought.</p>
            <p>The Diuine <hi>Chryſostome</hi> expoundeth it after this maner;<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Epiſt. ad. Epheſ. Ser. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> Redeeme the time (Bretheren) that is, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the opportunity &amp; the occaſion to doe good. Time is not yours to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and wherein with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinning you may play &amp; ſpend it away wickedly,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6055:124"/>or conſume it vnthriftily (as is ſaid of one, who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that hee could play a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his money, &amp; throwe it into the riuer if he liſted, becauſe hee was Maiſter thereof) for though it be yours, by being in your hands &amp; power to imploy it well or ill; Yet are you but Pilgrimes and Paſſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and therefore ought to deſire no worldly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, nor vaine glory, nor riches, dignities, puiſſance or authoritie, reuenge, nor any point or particle of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne or worſhip. Suffer &amp; beare meekly all things which offer themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you againſt the haire as
<pb facs="tcp:6055:125"/>it were, and diſagreeable to your good liking; haue patience therein, &amp; ſo you ſhall redeeme and ranſom <hi>Time,</hi> and doe good to your enemies, and giue them of that you haue if they aske it and be in neceſſitie. Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had a houſe moſt rich and moſt ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, very coſtly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and well orderly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and prepared, and that by the fame &amp; report ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of certaine theeues or bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glarors did enter into the ſame, who ſought and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured to kill the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that afterwards they might ſpoile and rob him, whereupon hee ſhould ſay
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6055:125"/>vnto them, Oh my good friends, for the loue of God, doe not murther me, and I will yeeld and render you all that I haue in my houſe, and thereupon deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all things they aske and demaund; of ſuch a one wee may truly ſay, that himſelfe ranſomed his owne life: So after the ſame maner, thou (my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) enioyeſt a large faire houſe, greate ſtore of wealth, iewels, pearles, and precious ſtones; thou poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeſt a Soule which is <hi>the liuely Temple of the liuing God,</hi> yea his owne houſe and dwelling place, thou art endued with faith, hope
<pb facs="tcp:6055:126"/>and charitie, beſides other vertues and gifts from his hands and bountifull libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality; Giue and beſtowe all that ſhall be demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of thee, and looſe the remainder when it ſhall be expedient and needfull, in exchange leaſt thou looſe the life of thy Soule, and ſo thou mayeſt ranſome &amp; redeeme Time, which in caſe thou doſt not, thy enemies will leade thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way captiue.</p>
            <p>Againe, Sinners may redeeme and ranſome the time they with-held capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated, if they will embrace and follow the Counſell of the Prophet <hi>Baruch,</hi> where
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:6055:126"/>he ſayeth;<note place="margin">Baruch. 4 28.</note> 
               <hi>Sicut fuit ſenſus vester, &amp;c.</hi> Conuert and turne you to God, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your conuerſion to him by repentance, you ſhall ſerue and obey him tenne times more carefull with more ardent heate, feruour and diligence then before when you departed from him and miſimployed your time.</p>
            <p>They will likewiſe reſcue and repurchaſe the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if they wil performe the admonition which the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> giueth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring vpon the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of theſe words, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut exhibuistis membra ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Euen as hitherto
<pb facs="tcp:6055:127"/>you haue imployed &amp; yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your bodies, ſenſes, and members in the ſeruice of vncleanneſſe and iniquity, to ſin, now wheele about and looke back, turne ouer the leafe, and imploy all things to ſerue equity, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and holineſſe of life.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle hauing ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>Humanum dico propter infirmitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veſtram, &amp;c. I ſpeake as a man for your infirmities ſake,</hi> and becauſe you are weake, hartily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching you, that you wholy imploy and buſie your ſelues in the ſeruice of God by keeping his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Time (of which
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6055:127"/>holy exerciſe the fruite is your ſanctification, for by ſuch workes man doth ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie and dedicate himſelfe wholy to God) &amp; that you perform this with as great affection and alacritie, as euer hereto fore you deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your ſelues to impiety, yeelding your members as bondſlaues to ſinne, whoſe fruite is nothing elſe but iniquity, and wherof a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner can make no other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but that hee remaine a Sinner, a miſerable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man, and be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding it be true that Sanctification doth far exceed iniquitie,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:128"/>yet reſt I well ſatisfied with ſuch vnfained endeuor and reſolution of doing good workes, which ſome haue performed after their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, with ſuch earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as before they were ſet and bent to ſin by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing and offending of God; We ſee how violent and couragious many are to ſinne, and after they haue glutted their appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites how ſlothful and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme, howe ſlacke and faint they are to repent &amp; to exerciſe themſelues in actions of vertue? The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ruſheth through thick and thin to accompliſh his deſire, and to ſatisfie his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:6055:128"/>luſtfull appetite: and as it were to run away with that he longed for; nothing ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth difficult or hard vnto him; and if thou aske him, how canſt thou ſuffer this, or that? though he be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo graue and ancient, to all things he will frame an anſwer, and ſay, yes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Time</hi> ſeemeth moſt ſhort to ſinners for inioying of their luſts and pleaſures, but to occupie themſelues in good workes it ſeemes moſt large and weariſome: The Seruice long, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon large, his prayers, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, paines and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, laborious and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Cold weather makes
<pb facs="tcp:6055:129"/>them heartleſſe and cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, heate ſlacketh and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſeth them, and all things ſeemes painefull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie. So as (to conclude) that is a moſt ſingular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie and helpe for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme <hi>Time,</hi> to imploy it well, and to vſe it with ſuch alacritie, heedfulneſſe, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe and liuelineſſe to deuotion, as he hath done when he was altogether bent and reſolued to looſe and capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate to ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:6055:129"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> How it is to be vnderſtood that <hi>the dayes are euill,</hi> and howe that therefore <hi>TIME</hi> is to be redeemed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L things that God hath created are good being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in themſelues, and according to their owne nature and kind, becauſe that from his moſt bleſſed hands, there could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no worke or thing which were not good; And ſo himſelfe after the worke of Creation ſayd, that <hi>all were good and perfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.31,</note> 
               <hi>that
<pb facs="tcp:6055:130"/>he had made and created.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſpeake to our purpoſe, the dayes and yeares conſidered in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues cannot be euill, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can there be any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall malice found in them, which iuſtly may be tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a fault, becauſe they are not capable thereof: nor yet any feeling of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, for they cannot apprehend it, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſerie which men ſuffer for their ſinnes: But the dayes are ſayd to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, in reſpect of men, who liue in them by occaſion of their tranſgreſſions and ſins they commit, or by reaſon of thoſe puniſhments they
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:6055:130"/>ſuffer, cauſed by the former, according to <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>S. Ieromes</hi> expoſition.<note place="margin">Chryſ. &amp; Hier. ſup. Pſal. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> And ſo are perſons that be weake, ſicke, ſad, ſorowfull or afflicted, wont to ſay, O what an euill day this hath beene vnto me! oh how terrible, and how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter!</p>
            <p>Two things there are (ſaith that excellent <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>) that make the daies to be euill,<note place="margin">Aug. ſer. <hi>24.</hi> de verbis Apoſt.</note> &amp; are the cauſe wherefore they are termed euill, being indeed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues good, namely the <hi>Malice</hi> and the <hi>Miſerie</hi> of men: The miſerie or wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe is common, but the malice ought not ſo to
<pb facs="tcp:6055:131"/>be. From the time that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſinned, and was bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of Paradiſe, the dayes haue euer continued euill: and the crying of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants at the time of their birth is a preſage of their miſerie and troubles, and a ſure ſigne and infallible to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that vpon that day they enter into this vale of teares, and that at the leaſt (though they be ſo happie as to become good) they ſhall not faile but bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combred with ſundry dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous temptations and tryals, albeit the cauſe thereof cannot be expreſly declared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euthymius</hi> expounding<note place="margin">Euthym. in Pſal. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:6055:131"/>thoſe wordes of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Who is that man that wiſheth life and deſireth to ſee good dayes?</hi> ſaith, that thoſe good dayes, are they of the other life, for that thoſe of this, are euill, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſpake to <hi>Pharao,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 47.8.9.</note> and the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> alſo when he wrote to them of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Redeeme the time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe the dayes are euill.</hi> And <hi>S. Baſil</hi> faith the ſame: <hi>The whole time of my Piſgrimage</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iacob</hi> anſwering <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil, ibid.</note> who had asked him,<note place="margin">Gen. 47.9.</note> how old he was) <hi>is an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirty yeares fewe and euill haue the dayes of my life beene.</hi> The king deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:6055:132"/>him, how many are the yeares of thy life? and he anſwered, <hi>The dayes of my pilgrimage, &amp;c.</hi> and though it ſeemes that he anſwered not to the purpoſe, yet did he anſwer moſt admirably, like a moſt holy, wiſe and diſcreet <hi>Saint,</hi> amending and ſecretly correcting the demaund and queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto him, euen as the Maiſter is accuſtomed to doe with his Diſciple, when he demaundeth not aright: who gaue <hi>Pharao</hi> to vnderſtand, that the yeares of mans life, are not yeares, but dayes, and the dayes be not dayes but houres, and the houres, not houres, but
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:6055:132"/>moments; and that the life of the Seruants of God, is no ſteedfaſt or permanent life, but only a peregrinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pilgrimage towards the heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> They are paſſengers and ſtrangers, and thereafter they vſe the goods of this world; and ſayde further, that the daies he liued were few, being a hundred and thirty yeares, becauſe theſe and many more, are indeed but few,<note place="margin">Gen. 29. &amp; 31. Iob. 7.</note> likes as the longeſt life, is but ſhort.</p>
            <p>And finally he cals his dayes <hi>euill,</hi> becauſe of the manifold perils wherein he remembred himſelfe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes plunged, and of
<pb facs="tcp:6055:133"/>the corporall and ſpirituall trauels which vſually hee ſuffered: For the life of man is a temptation and tryall euen all the time that he liues vpon the earth. And becauſe of the miſery and troubles, the miſchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and diſgraces which <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall and happen vnto men in their dayes,</hi> happen and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall men in their time, the dayes are called <hi>euill,</hi> as likewiſe in the ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they are ſo tearmed.</p>
            <p>Therefore alſo is the day of Iudgement called the euill and the bitter day,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 50.</note> in reſpect of the wicked; and from hence we may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſence and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:6055:133"/>of thoſe words of our Sauiour written by <hi>S. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6.34.</note> 
               <hi>Be not ouer carefull for the morrow, for the morrow ſhall care for it ſelfe; the day hath inough with his owne griefe:</hi> That is,<note place="margin">Simon de Caſsià.</note> as if more plainely he had ſayde, Too day yee haue ſufficient to do, namely to carke and care for this preſent day, and for all the labors, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyles, occupations, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities &amp; buſineſſes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, without doubling the waight or ouer-charging your ſelues, in taking vpon you too day, the anguiſh, vexation and burthen of the morrowe, imagining that then you may do it, or
<pb facs="tcp:6055:134"/>that then ſuch a thing may happen vnto you: for I aſſure you that to morrow will be very carefull of it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And therefore the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wrote to them of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> when he ſayd, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the time becauſe the dayes are euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe, 5.16.</note> was this, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, that the dayes are troubleſome, full of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, difficulties and lets, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations, temptations &amp; impediments of your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and health; For the which, and for many other things and affaires, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into the neceſſities of this body and life, &amp; our owne
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:6055:134"/>ill inclined naturall diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition after the fall haue leade vs, much part of time is often loſt without fruite, and is ſold, morgaged, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pawned, pledged and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuated. And therefore I hartily beſeech and exhort you, and do highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to your charge, that you take ſpeciall care and regard that it be not ill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed any longer, nor withheld impriſoned, but that you cauſe and procure to your vttermoſt power and endeuor, that thereby you may reape profit, that it be redeemed, repurcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ranſomed, and that you will duly eſteeme ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:6055:135"/>and negotiate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; So as when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſhall come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand an Account, thou mayeſt be able to make it good. And ſo are all of vs to do and performe, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering beſides that the dayes are moſt ſhort, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine and irreuocable, we ſhould be couetous of Time, endeuoring and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing to recouer that which is loſt, and to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them vnto whome we haue done any harme by making of great haſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and ſaue that which is to come to ſerue God in, and to repaire our former negligences and paſſed
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6055:135"/>heedleſſnes with preſent diligence and care, renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and augmenting our repentance, mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and charitable deeds: Euen as accuſtometh the Trauellor to doe when he hath any long iourney to make, and perceiuing the time to be ſhort, and that by his owne negligence, rechleſnes and careleſnes, he is much behind, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoreth afterwards to runne in ſuch ſort that hee goeth in two houres ſo much way as that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hee would not haue gone in ſixe, and for that purpoſe lookes for neerer wayes and ſhorter cuts, he
<pb facs="tcp:6055:136"/>ſweats and toyles, and runs on headlong a thouſand rugged wayes, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting or pawſing, though neceſſitie much require it, and if he hap to eate, it will be but a bit, and that with much celerity and quicke ſpeed.</p>
            <p>So did the ſame Apoſtle for the redeeming of the Time which he had loſt, &amp; withheld captiuated. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor ſi quomodo comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.12. 1. Cor. 9.24</note> As if he had ſayde, Now in reſpect I captiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and loſt ſo much time, and erred ſo farre, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo backwards in the right path of Gods ſeruice, and was ſo negligent in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6055:136"/>gaining and procuring the glorie of the life to come, I will now giue double di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and beſtir my ſelfe apace, and runne without any looking backe, becauſe I make no reckoning of all that I haue already iourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed and traced, but rather will commit all that to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuion, as if I had not tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled it at all, crowding and thruſting my ſelfe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as it were through the middeſt of all that ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, hauing alwayes an eye to that which I haue to go, and not to that, which I haue already trauelled.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Dauid</hi> did the ſame, after that God had ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:6055:137"/>and enlarged his heart with his loue and feare, and tooke away thoſe gifes or fetters which he had on his feet, as himſelfe confeſſeth, ſaying;<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119.</note> 
               <hi>Viam mandatorum tuorum cucurri, &amp;c.</hi> When as by thy great mercy (O my Lorde God) thou thoughteſt good to drawe me out of my ſinne and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, wherein I detained &amp; ſpent ſo much time, and haſt bene pleaſed to burſt the chaines where with I was tied and bound, refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and comforting my heart with the water of thy ſuperabundant grace, more then of Angels; I begunne (for the redeeming of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6055:137"/>Time captiuated) to runne, and haue runned (as farre forth as I could) with all diligence, without reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it were, one breath or other, the way of thy precepts.</p>
            <p>The deuoute and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Thaulerus</hi> (with whom we wil conclude this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) did aske,<note place="margin">Thauler.</note> how loſt and paſſed Time might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and raunſomed, conſidering wee haue no moment of time which we owe not to God, and (as <hi>Gregory Niſsenus</hi> ſaieth) when all the life is implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed in Prayer,<note place="margin">Greg. Niſſ. in orat. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie.</note> &amp; in giuing thanks to God, with much ado, do we accompliſh as
<pb facs="tcp:6055:138"/>we ought, what at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ouerrunnes vs, how much leſſe that of the Time paſt, and to come: maketh anſwer thus; Let euery one depart and retire himſelfe withall poſſible power and ſtrength, from all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place and time, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelfe wholy vnto that preſent <hi>Nuno</hi> (which properly cannot be ſayd in the vulgar language) of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, where God is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially, &amp; always co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in one <hi>Being,</hi> and in one firme ſtability, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of any thing that is <hi>Paſt,</hi> or <hi>To come,</hi> but all <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> and in one perperuale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, vniforine, perdurable,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6055:138"/>fixed, permanent, conſtant, vnchangeable &amp; vnmoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, hauing no time to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſſe him, In whom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth &amp; is al preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, paſt &amp; future, &amp; all beginning and end of time, without beginning &amp; without end. And there in God are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all the treaſures which by the wicked are vilified, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpifed &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, yea infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit moe. And they who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome many times to lift them aboue themſelues, &amp; aboue all things created, &amp; to hide themſelues and make their neſts and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with God, who abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the Soules of all preſent, ſuch without
<pb facs="tcp:6055:139"/>doubt do make themſelues rich, and ſhall finde in him much more of that which otherwiſe they might haue loſt. And in this introuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or conuerſion to God, ought euery one of vs, wholy, entirely and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to transforme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into him, and from the very bowels of his heart ſay vnto him after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Oh my euerlaſting God, If all the TIME which hath bene from the beginning of the world, and which ſhall be till the end, were granted vnto me, I would liue wholy for thee and in thy ſeruice, and from
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:6055:139"/>henceforth I would God I might liue and continue ſo loyal, faithfull &amp; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in all kind of vertue, as all as many men as haue bene borne and liued, though it be in all manner affliction, tryall, miſery &amp; tribulation. I would to God that all the waters of the Sea might be diſtilled through my eies to remedy al them that are poore and in neceſſitie, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them that are ſad and heauie, and to loue thee (my God) to praiſe thee, to extoll thee, to magnifie thee, and to glorifie thee ſo much as all thy Saints and Angels of thy ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb facs="tcp:6055:140"/>Court: For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt I would doe and performe all thoſe things very willingly and with all my heart.</p>
            <p>And certainely he that retaineth and feeleth in his hart that will and liuely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ſhall be ſo aſſured that he ſhal be accepted of that moſt iuſt and rightfull Iudge, as if he had put it in effect, becauſe the ſeeking with an vnfained will to accompliſh and performe any thing,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>19.</hi> in Matth. S. Tho. <hi>1.2.</hi> qu <hi>20.</hi> art <hi>4 2. Cor. 8.12</hi>
               </note> and the reall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and fulfilling thereof, is all one and the very ſame with God. <hi>For</hi> as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>if there be firſt a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mind, it is accepted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:6055:140"/>to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
